<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The communicants instructor. Or, A sacramental catechism in which the nature of the covenant of grace, and the visible seals thereof (viz.) baptism and the Lord's Supper, with the gospel qualifications of worthy receivers, are opened with all plainness and clearness by way of question and answer. Recommended to the use of the younger and more ignorant sort, especially to such as desire admission to, and would worthily partake of the Lord's Supper; with a request to the charitable, that they would make it a piece of their spiritual alms to the poor. By George Day, Minister of the gospel.</title>
            <author>Day, George, d. 1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229671</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895489</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152928</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82009)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152928)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2334:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The communicants instructor. Or, A sacramental catechism in which the nature of the covenant of grace, and the visible seals thereof (viz.) baptism and the Lord's Supper, with the gospel qualifications of worthy receivers, are opened with all plainness and clearness by way of question and answer. Recommended to the use of the younger and more ignorant sort, especially to such as desire admission to, and would worthily partake of the Lord's Supper; with a request to the charitable, that they would make it a piece of their spiritual alms to the poor. By George Day, Minister of the gospel.</title>
                  <author>Day, George, d. 1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 102, [12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst a[t] the Bible and Three Crowns in Cheapside nea[r] Mercers-Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With three final leaves of advertisements.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dr. Williams' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Last Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Communicants Inſtructor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, A SACRAMENTAL <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> IN WHICH The Nature of the Covenant of Grace, and the viſible Seals thereof <hi>(viz.)</hi> Baptiſm and the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, with the Goſpel Qualifications of worthy Receivers, are opened with all plainneſs and clearneſs by way of Queſtion and Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Recommended to the Uſe of the Younger and more Ignorant ſort, eſpecially to ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Admiſſion to, and would worthily Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Lord's Supper; with a Requeſt to the Charitable, That they would make it a Piece of their Spiritual Alms to the Poor.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Day,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 5.12.</hi>
               </bibl> For when for the time ye ought to be Teachers, ye have need that one teach you again which be the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God, and are become ſuch as have need of Milk, and not of ſtrong Meat.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:2"/>
            <head>The EPISTLE to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THO' Baptiſm and the Supper of the Lord be ſacred Ordinances, and Chriſt's own Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, yet ſuch is the ſin and ſhame of this degenerate Age, That Multitudes under the Chriſtian Profeſſion live in a careleſs Omiſſion of them, and not a few in a prophane Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mpt and Oppoſition againſt them. The Fault of the former ſort proceeds from groſs Ignorance of the ſpiritual Nature, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, and Ends of theſe Ordinances: That of the latter, from a Spirit prepoſſeſſed and prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with Error.</p>
            <p>Now, tho' I have little hopes of doing any good upon the Erronious by this brief and ſlender Piece, ſeeing their Malignity againſt the Truths which they diſown, will (probably) encline them to reject it with diſdain on the firſt ſight of the Title Page, without vouchſafing it a ſober peruſal; yet the hopes of being ſomewhat ſerviceable to the Ignorant, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to ſuch as are deſirous of ſpiritual Knowledge, and are willing to be inſtructed, have at length pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with me to comply with the Requeſt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Friends, in expoſing this mean Eſſay to publick View.</p>
            <p>I know there are many excellent Helps of this
<pb facs="tcp:152928:3"/>kind already extant, and therefore this may well be thought needleſs; and I confeſs, this very Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hath ſuppreſſed theſe Meditations for many years, by me; but obſerving divers Tracts that ſpeak much of the Lord's Supper, ſay little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Baptiſm, (tho' this being the initiating Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and firſt ſeal of the Goſpel Covenant, ought firſt to be conſidered, and well underſtood) I have therefore endeavoured to open both theſe holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances diſtinctly, together with the Nature of the Covenant of Grace, to which they are annexed, as its viſible ſigns and ſeals.</p>
            <p>I have made it my Buſineſs to gather the moſt material and ſoul-concerning Truths that I find ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in many excellent Authors, that have written on this Subject, and contracted them, that I might give thee much in a little, and croud as much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Matter into theſe few Pages as I well could, without prejudice to the ſenſe, and with due regard to weaker Memories, that a little Pains and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may make much Truth thine own.</p>
            <p>I have alſo endeavoured to expreſs my ſenſe of things with the greatest plainneſs and clearneſs I could, uſing words and phraſes that may eaſily be underſtood by perſons of mean Capacity, and ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly declining others; having obſerved in Teaching both Young and Old, that the want of underſtanding the true meaning, tho' but of one word in a Sentence, hath made the whole unintelligible, and ſo unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them.</p>
            <p>Thou wilt find to most of the Anſwers ſcripture Proofs ſubjoined, tho' only referr'd to, for brevities ſake, therefore pray turn to them, and ſee with thine own eyes how clearly and fully theſe Truths are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the holy Scriptures, and ſo the reaſon why
<pb facs="tcp:152928:3"/>thou ſhould'st believe them; for we ought to make no Poſition or Aſſertion an Article of our Chriſtian Faith, but what is founded on a Divine Atteſtation, and bottomed on the written Word of God, which is the only, perfect, and perpetual Rule of our Chriſtian Faith and Practice.</p>
            <p>I have purpoſely choſen to give thee this Help in a Catechiſtical method, by way of Queſtion and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe it is the moſt eaſie, plain familiar way of inſtructing the Ignorant, and therefore like to he the more profitable.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe it is of great Antiquity, having been uſed not only in the Christian, but alſo in the Jewiſh Church, yea, ſome of the Learned trace its Foot ſteps back to the beginning of time, concluding, that it was practiſed by <hi>Adam</hi> himſelf, who catechiſed or inſtructed his Sons in the Doctrine of Man's Fall, of the Seed of the Woman, and of worſhipping of God by offering ſacrifices, &amp;c. [Read <hi>Willet, Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Greenham, Pemble,</hi> and others on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.]</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe the neglect of Catechiſing for <hi>20</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> years last past (which we ſhould reflect on with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame and grief) hath been one great cauſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecay of Knowledge in our days; there being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y thouſands of adult and grown Perſons, [and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of them Parents and Governours of Families] <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſly ignorant of the very Fundamentals of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſtian Faith which they profeſs; and that tho' me of them have ſate under the preaching of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord a long time. Indeed, 'tis an Obſervation I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve often made, and am confirmed in it by daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erience, That uncatechiſed Heads underſtand but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittle of the moſt excellent Sermons they bear, and
<pb facs="tcp:152928:4"/>therefore it is not to be thought ſtrange, that they grow little the wiſer by them. O that this were du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, and might prove a cogent Argument to Ministers and Governours of Families for the Revival of this uſeful Exerciſe among us!</p>
            <p>And (becauſe my words may have little weight) let me here take leave humbly to mind my Reverend Brethren of a ſerious and weighty Paſſage of a great Divine now in Glory.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouble</hi> Vind. Grat. Praef. p. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>I could heartily wiſh</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that thoſe [Miniſters] among us, whom either Eaſe or Pride have made careleſs in this Office [of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>chiſing] would be pleas'd to look abroad into ſuch Congregations, where this courſe is held, and to compare them with their own and others, where 'tis neglected; they ſhould ſoon perceive how fair and open a paſſage is made for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to follow after, where diligent Catechiſing hath gone before; and on the other ſide, how hopeleſs their Endeavours is, who labour to imprint in the Heads of their People the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Concluſions before they have learned the Principles of Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If theſe Men complain and ſay, We have ſpent our ſtrength in vain, and our Labour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out profit, preaching long, and ſeeing little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; I will not pity them, who are lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unwiſe Nurſes, that, when their Children thrive not, lay the Blame upon their ſickly Bodies when the Fault is in their own indiſcretion, who feed them not with Childrens Bread, but forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon them ſtronger Meat, which they canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> digeſt, but vomit up again.</hi> (Thus he.)</p>
            <p>To this hearty wiſh of his I ſubjoyn another, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:4"/>all the Paſtors of Churches may fully and faithfully obey that Precept of the Chief Shepherd, <hi>John 21.15, 16.</hi> requiring them to feed his Lambs as well as his Sheep.</p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe with a word or two of Counſel; (Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) if thou art yet weak in ſpiritual Knowledge, and willing to be inſtructed, that thou mayſt be made wiſe to Salvation, let me beſeech thee to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this faithful Advice.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Labour for a diſtinct and methodical Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the great Foundation-Truths of the Chriſtian Religion, thoſe first Principles of the Oracles of God, drawn up to thine hand in many more general Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms; eſpecially I recommend to thy uſe that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Catechiſm of the Aſſembly of Divines, both ſhorter and larger; a little Labour will commit the leſſer to thy memory, and read the other with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to explain that, with Mr. <hi>Lyes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>littles,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Vincents</hi> Explanations. The Knowledge of theſe Truths will prepare thee to read the holy Scriptures, and hear Sermons with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Profit.</p>
            <p>Next, I offer thee the ſerious peruſal of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Catechiſm, in the compoſure of which I have purpoſely left out ſeveral Queſtions very proper to have been inſerted, becauſe they are already an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the Aſſemblies Catechiſm. Say not thou art too old to learn a Catechiſm (if ignorant) unleſs thou thinkeſt thy ſelf alſo too old to go to Heaven, and ſo too old to learn the way thither. Be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of uſing the means to get Knowledge, but be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhamed of thy Ignorance, and bluſh to bear a Child of Seven years old, that hath been well catechiſed, give a better account of the Chriſtian Faith than many of <hi>30, 40,</hi> or of <hi>50</hi> years of Age can do.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:6"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Pray earneſtly and daily for the inward teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God's holy Spirit in and with the outward teachings of the Word; without this, tho tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may'ſt fill thy Head with the Notions of Truth, ye thou wilt never feel the ſaving Impreſſions of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on thy heart, but remain a ſtranger to the life an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power of Godlineſs. Read thoſe precious promiſes and humbly plead them in prayer, <hi>Prov. 1.23. Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 59.21. Luk. 11.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> And laſtly, Believe the Truths which thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>earnt, and live according to the Rule of them. Le Knowledge and Practice (as an holy Taine) g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd in hand, and ſtilt keep pace each with other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h of them are required as neceſſary qualification to entitle thee to true happineſs, <hi>John 13 17.</hi> O d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not aim at any thing ſhort of that! The Experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and Practical Chriſtian will be found to be the wiſeſt and best in the great diſcriminating Day. Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou may'ſt be ſuch an one, and that thy Meditation may contribute ſomewhat thereto, is the ſincere an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fervent Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb. 19. 1691.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine and the Churche in Chriſt,</hi> George Day.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152928:6"/>
            <head>A SACRAMENTAL <hi>Catechiſm.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>WHat is a Sacarment in general?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Sacrament is an holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Divine Inſtitution, annexed to the Covenants which God hath made with Men, wherein by outward and ſenſible ſigns the Promiſes of the Covenant are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, ſealed, and applied to God's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-people, and they are bound to obey him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</p>
            <p>Q. 2. <hi>Are theſe Ordinances call'd by the name of Sacraments in the holy Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. Yet ſeeing it is a word very fit to ſignifie the thing to which it is applied, it may lawfully be uſed.</p>
            <p>Q. 3. <hi>What is the original and proper ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the word [Sacrament]?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152928:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As it was uſed of old in a civil ſenſe, it ſignified an Oath taken in War by Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to their General, whereby they were bound to perform the Duties of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>Q. 4. <hi>Why are the Seals of God</hi>'s <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants called Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe by our receiving them we are bound (as it were) by an Oath to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Duties of God's Covenant-peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Q. 5. <hi>What are the parts of a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two. The one is an outward viſible ſign, or thing ſignifying, which may be ſeen by the Eye of the Body; as Water in Baptiſm, and Bread and Wine in the Lord's Supper. The other is the inward and ſpiritual grace, or thing ſignified, which can only be ſeen by the Eye of the Soul, or by Faith, and that is Chriſt with all his ſaving Benefits, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29.</p>
            <p>Q. 6. <hi>Do all thoſe who receive the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſigns receive the inward grace alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. For wicked and graceleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may receive the outward ſigns, but not the inward grace with them; none but true believers receive them both.</p>
            <p>Q. 7. <hi>What is a Covenant in the general?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152928:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Covenant is a ſolemn Contract or Agreement between ſeveral perſons, two at the leaſt, wherein they do mutually bind themſelves each to other, in certain Articles, to both their Contents, and uſually confirmed by ſigns and ſeals, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.27. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18 3.</p>
            <p>Q 8. <hi>Hath God ever made a Covenant with Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. Tho God be infinitely above Man, yet he hath been pleaſed, through condeſcending grace, to deal with Man in this familiar way of Covenanting, as a Man with his Friend, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.18.</p>
            <p>Q. 9. <hi>VVhat Covenants hath God made with Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two eſpecially. The firſt called the Covenant of Works. The ſecond, The Covenant of Grace, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Q. 10. <hi>What is the Covenant of Works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That Covenant which God made with our firſt Parents, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> in the eſtate of Innocence, and in them, with all their Children, wherein God promiſed perfect happineſs to them, upon Condition of their perfect Obedience to him; and threatned them with Death on their Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16, 17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 11. <hi>Why is this called the Covenant of Works?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152928:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it required the Works of Man's Obedience to the whole Law of God, as the Condition of his Life and Happineſs, <hi>Lev.</hi> 18.5.</p>
            <p>Q. 12. <hi>Had our firſt Parents ſufficient ſtrength to perform that Condition, and keep that Covenant with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. Our firſt Parents being crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upright and perfect, had ſufficient power to perform perfect Obedience to the Law of God, and ſo to keep his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29.</p>
            <p>Q. 13. <hi>Did our firſt Parents keep their Covenant with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. Our firſt Parents brake their Covenant with God, by complying with the Temptation of Satan in eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit, and thereby brought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and all the Children deſcending from them by ordinary Generation, into an eſtate of ſin and miſery, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>begin. Rom.</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 14. <hi>Doth God ſuffer</hi> Adam <hi>and all his Children to periſh in their ſinful and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. God did of his own free grace from all Eternity elect ſome of fall'n Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to everlaſting life, and gave them to Jeſus Chriſt, that they might be recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſaved by him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152928:8"/>
            <p>Q. 15. <hi>Did the Lord Jeſus Chriſt then undertake to be a Saviour to them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. There was an Eternal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, or Agreement between God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and God the Son (which is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the Covenant of Redemption) wherein God the Father gave the Elect unto God the Son, as to a Redeemer, and he engaged to perform the work of their Redemption, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.20, 21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.3, 4, 19, 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. 16. <hi>Did God make another Covenant with Man after the firſt was broken?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. God was pleaſed to make a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Covenant with Man, called the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.2, 7.</p>
            <p>Q. 17. <hi>VVhat is this Covenant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Covenant of Grace is that which God made with Man in his fall'n &amp; ſinful ſtate wherein God, thro' the Merits and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, promiſeth Pardon and Life unto all penitent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ſinners, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. and 16.30.</p>
            <p>Q. 18. <hi>VVhy is this call'd the Covenant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe all that is promiſed in it is the fruit of God's free grace in Chriſt to ſinners. 2. Becauſe it is the free grace of God that inclined God to make it, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152928:9"/>that perſwades and enables us to conſent to it, and to keep it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p>Q. 19. <hi>What is the condition of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant on Man's part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The great comprehenſive Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, which, (if it be true and ſaving) is accompanied with Repentance, and all other Graces in the Heart, and brings forth new Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the Life, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.21. <hi>James</hi> 2.18.</p>
            <p>Q 20. <hi>How can it be call'd a Covenant of Grace, if it is Conditional?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Very well. For, 1. It is an Act of God's free grace, and infinite Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in God to make a Covenant with Man his Creature, whatever the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be. 2. The Condition it ſelf is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Faith in Chriſt. 3. God himſelf hath graciouſly undertaken for both Parts of the Covenant, his own and ours too, and by his grace perſwades and enables us to conſent to the Covenant, and perform the condition of it.</p>
            <p>Q. 21. <hi>Is any Man able to perform this Condition in his own ſtrength?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. we are in our natural ſtate both unwilling to conſent to, and unable to perform the Condition of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152928:9"/>but God is pleaſed to make his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect both willing and able by his ſpecial Grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. and 12.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13.</p>
            <p>Q. 22. <hi>What are the Differences between the Covenant of Works, and the Covenant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe Ten eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Covenant of Works was made between God and the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> with all his Natural Seed, <hi>i.e.</hi> all Mankind. But the Covenant of Grace was made between God and the ſecond <hi>Adam, i.e.</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and all his Spiritual Seed, <hi>i e.</hi> All God's Elect, which are only ſome of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Q. 23. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. That was made with Man in a ſtate of Innocency: This was made with Man in a ſtate of ſin.</p>
            <p>Q. 24. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. The Condition of that, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Obedience; the Condition of this, is Faith.</p>
            <p>Q. 25. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. Under that, Man was entruſted with the keeping of himſelf, and his own happineſs; under this, he is kept by the power of God.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152928:10"/>
            <p>Q. 26. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 5. Under that, Man was to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by his own Righteouſneſs; under this, by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. 27. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 6. Under that, the leaſt ſin was a breach of the Covenant; under this, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Unbelief and final Perſeverance therein, is a breach of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>Q. 28. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 7. That promiſed not pardon to the ſinner upon Repentance, this doth.</p>
            <p>Q. 29. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 8. That was of uſe only for a little time, untill Man's Fall; this hath been of uſe ever ſince, and will be to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>Q. 30. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 9. That was eſpecially deſigned for the glory of God's Juſtice; this for the Glory of God's Mercy.</p>
            <p>Q. 31. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 10. That had no Mediator, or Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; this hath a Mediator and Surety, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. 32. <hi>VVhat doth Chriſt do as Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of the Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt, as Mediator of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, being himſelf both God and Man,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152928:10"/>performs the great Work of Reconciling God and Man, whom ſin had made Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and brings them into a Covenant of Grace and Peace each with other, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.6. <hi>c.</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p>Q. 33. <hi>VVhat doth Chriſt do as the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rety of the Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt as the Surety of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, undertakes to ſee the Covenant faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and fully performed; <hi>i e.</hi> That God ſhall perform his Promiſes to his Elect; and that they ſhall perform the condition of the Covenant unto God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.22.</p>
            <p>Q. 34. <hi>Hath the Covenant of Grace been always the ſame, or divers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> The Covenant of Grace hath been always the ſame, as to the Subſtance of it, but it hath been different as to the manner of its Adminiſtration or Diſpenſation, &amp; ſo is diſtinguiſhed into the Old &amp; New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.13.</p>
            <p>Q. 35. <hi>Which is called the Old Covenant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That which was Adminiſtred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>Q. 36. <hi>Which is call'd the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That which is Adminiſtred ſince the Coming of Chriſt in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152928:11"/>
            <p>Q. 37. <hi>VVherein doth the Adminiſtration of the New Covenant differ from that of the Old?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. In the eaſineſs of it. That was Adminiſtred by Promiſes, Propheſies, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and other Types, which were coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, painful, and burthenſome Sacrific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: But this is adminiſtred by the preaching of the Word, and diſpenſing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Baptiſm and the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per which are ſewer in number, and more e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſily performed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9.</p>
            <p>Q. 38. <hi>VVherein elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> 2. In the clearneſs of it. That was Adminiſtred by dark Types and Figures, which were ſhadows of good things then to come; but this is Adminiſtred by light and clear Ordinances, by which Chriſt and his Benefits are more plainly revealed to us, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.1. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>Q. 39. <hi>VVherein elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. In the efficacy and power of it. That was weak and unprofitable incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of this: Becauſe the Spirit of God was not given to the Church in ſo large a meaſure before Chriſt, as it is ſince, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17. <hi>John</hi> 7.39.</p>
            <p>Q. 40. <hi>VVherein elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. In the viſible Seals of it. That had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152928:11"/>Circumciſion, &amp; the Paſſover, for its Seals; this hath Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. 41. <hi>VVherein elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 5. In the Latitude and Extent of it. That extended peculiarly to the Jews; this extends both to the Jews and Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34, 35, 36.</p>
            <p>Q. 42. <hi>VVherein elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 6. In the Duration and Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it. That was to continue but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Chriſt came in the Fleſh; but this is to continue untill Chriſt comes in glory.</p>
            <p>Q. 43. <hi>Who changed the Adminiſtration of the Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who is the only Head, and Lawgiver of his Church, and ſo hath power to Alter or Add, lay aſide, or ſet up ſuch Laws and Ordinances in it as he pleaſeth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9, 10. <hi>James</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 44. <hi>VVhy did Chriſt change the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For his own glory, and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches good; for</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe Ordinances under the Old Covenant were more dark, difficult, coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and weak, than theſe under the New Covenant.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152928:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Ordinances became unſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and unſerviceable to the Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt's coming in the fleſh, becauſe they ſignified Chriſt to come; therefore when Chriſt, the Subſtance of them, was come, thoſe Sadows muſt be done away.</p>
            <p>Q. 45. <hi>How hath God confirmed the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God hath confirmed it by 4 things:
<list>
                  <item>1. By his Word of Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.</item>
                  <item>2. By his Oath, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.13, 14, 17, 18.</item>
                  <item>3. By the death of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.16, 17.</item>
                  <item>4. By the Signs and Seals of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Q. 46. <hi>VVhat are the Signs and Seals of the New covenant of grace now in Goſpel days?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Signs and Seals of the New Covenant, are Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. 47. <hi>VVhy are theſe Ordinances called Signs and Seals of the Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are of the ſame ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and uſe to the Covenant of Grace, as Signs and Seals put to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants between Man and Man uſe to be.</p>
            <p>Q. 48. <hi>VVhat is their ſignification, &amp; uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe Ordinances, as Signs, do ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152928:12"/>the Grace and Good-will of God in Chriſt to his Covenant-people; and as Seals do confirm, conveigh and apply the Grant of the Covenant, or a Right to all the Bleſſings promiſed therein to Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, and their engagement to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.</p>
            <p>Q. 49. <hi>Do theſe Sacraments certainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ork grace in all that receive them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. It is evident that many of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe who are baptized, and have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the Lord's Supper, live and dye in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aceleſs ſtate, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.23. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.26, 27.</p>
            <p>Q 50. <hi>Who then do receive ſaving bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe only receive ſaving benefit the Sacraments to whom the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of God doth bleſs them, working in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d by them on their Hearts, as he doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all God's Elect, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p>Q. 51. <hi>What is Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſm is an holy Ordinance of friſt, wherein the waſhing with Water, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or into the Name of the Father, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and the Holy Ghoſt, ſignifies and ſeals <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ingrafting into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Remiſſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by his Blood, and Regeneration by Spirit, and whereby the Perſons bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed are ſolemnly entred into the viſible
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152928:13"/>
               <hi>Church,</hi> and into an open and profeſſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to be wholly and only God's Covenant-people, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5.</p>
            <p>Q. 52. <hi>What be the Parts of Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are two. The outward and viſible part ſignifying; and the inward and ſpiritual part ſignified.</p>
            <p>Q 53. <hi>What is the outward ſignifying part of Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The outward ſignifying part of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm conſiſts in the waſhing the Body with the Element of Water, and the uſe of the words of Inſtitution, <hi>i e. Baptizing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. 54. <hi>What is the inward part ſignifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the outward ſigns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. By the waſhing with Water i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſignified two things; the waſhing awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the guilt of our ſins, or our Pardon and Juſtification procured by the blood o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the waſhing away of the filt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſin, or our Sanctification by the Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the work of Regeneration <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. <hi>John</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By the words of Inſtitution, <hi>i e.</hi> Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing in the Name of the Father, Son, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Holy Ghoſt, two things are alſo ſignifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That Miniſters have Authori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152928:13"/>both from God the Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt to adminiſter Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Perſons baptized do enter into an holy Covenant with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; <hi>i e.</hi> They take this only living and true God to be their own and only God, and give up themſelves, (if grown Perſons) or are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up by their Parents (if Infants) to this God, to be his Covenant-ſervants, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5.</p>
            <p>Q. 55. <hi>What are the ſpecial Ends of Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſpecial Ends of Baptiſm are of two ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as reſpect God; and ſo it is to be (1.) A Sign to ſignifie the Grace of the Covenant; and (2.) A Seal to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Grant of the Covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as reſpect Man; and ſo it is to be (1.) A Badge of our Chriſtian Profeſſion; (2.) A Bond to oblige us to perform the Duties of the <hi>Covenant, Gal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p>Q. 56. <hi>To whom is Baptiſm to be Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſm is not to be adminiſtred to any that are out of the viſible Church of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152928:14"/>
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> until they are inſtructed in the Chriſtian Religion, and profeſs Faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Obedience unto him: But the Infants of ſuch as are Members of the viſible <hi>Church</hi> are to be baptized, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 10. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39.</p>
            <p>Q. 57. <hi>How may it be proved that the Infants of Church-Members have a Right to Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It may be proved by theſe Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By their Covenant Relation to God. Thoſe that are in Covenant have a right to the Signs and Seals of the Covenant: But the Children of believing Parents are in Covenant, Therefore they have a right to the Signs and Seals of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Q. 58. <hi>Have Infants then a Right to the Lord's Supper alſo, and ſhould they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Infants of Believers have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, tho' not an immediate and actual right to the Lord's Supper, &amp; therefore may not receive it in their Infancy, for want of a capacity to diſcern the Lord's Body, or to underſtand the Nature, Uſe and Ends of that Ordinance, and to uſe it accordingly.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152928:14"/>
            <p>Q. 59. <hi>Should they not then be kept from Baptiſm alſo for the ſame Reaſon, ſeeing they underſtand not that Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. For they are as capable of Receiving this Ordinance of Baptiſm, as the Jewiſh Infants were of Circumciſion at 8 days old, and ought to be baptized, becauſe Baptiſm comes in the room of Circumciſion; and as that was the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Initiation or Entrance into the Church, and into the Covenant, ſo is this, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 60. <hi>By what other Argument is it proved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. By the Command of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt requiring his Apoſtles, and in them all Goſpel-Miniſters, to Diſciple all Nations, Baptizing them; and Infants are a very conſiderable part of Nations.</p>
            <p>Q. 61. <hi>But muſt they not believe firſt, and then be baptized, as</hi> Mark 16.16? <hi>And how can Infants believe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Adult or grown Perſons without the Church, muſt firſt be inſtructed in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and believe in him before they are admitted to Baptiſm, as <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.38, 39, 40, 41. But the Infants of Church-Members may be baptized, tho' they do not actually believe, becauſe they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152928:15"/>are the Children of Believers, ſeeing Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are parts of their Parents, &amp; are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted but as one Perſon with them, both by the Laws of God and Man, as the Root &amp; Branches are but one Tree, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 62. <hi>By what other Argument is it proved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. By the Example and Practice of the Apoſtles in the Primitive Church, who baptized whole Houſholds, and the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Practice of the Chriſtian Church in all Ages ever ſince, which hath been the ſame, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15, 33. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 63. <hi>What is the Duty of thoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents who offer their Children to God in Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Their Duty is, 1. To make a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Profeſſion of their Faith in God, the Father, Son, and Spirit, and Obedience to him according to his Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To own and renew the Covenant which they made with God in their own Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To conſent in the Name and behalf of their Children, (being parts of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) that they ſhall be the Lord's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venan-ſervants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To bring their Children up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord, to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152928:15"/>teach them the Nature of that Covenant with God which they make in Baptiſm by their Parents conſent, and to command them to keep it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.9.</p>
            <p>Q. 64. <hi>Is Baptiſm to be administred by dippin or ſprinkling?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſm may be adminiſtred either by dipping or ſprinkling: For, 1. The O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal word ſignifieth to waſh, whether by dipping or ſprinkling, as <hi>Mark</hi> 7.4.2. The Chriſtian Churches have uſed both.</p>
            <p>Q 65. <hi>Where ſhould Baptiſm be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſm being a Publick or Church-Ordinance, by which Perſons are ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addmitted into the Church of Chriſt, ſhould ordinarily be adminiſtred in the Publick Aſſemblies of Chriſtians, that thereby,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The whole Aſſembly may joyn in Prayer for a bleſſing upon the Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ptized, may be put in mind of the Covenant which they made in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Baptiſm, and be ſtirred up to keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Q 66. <hi>May <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in Priv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, in caſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceſſity; (as in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152928:16"/>times of Perſecution, or of the ſickneſs of the Perſons to be baptized, <hi>&amp;c</hi>) It may be adminiſtred in private Families, provided there be a competent number of other Chriſtians preſent to be witneſſes of the Adminiſtration, and to joyn in Prayer for a Bleſſing, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. and 16.33.</p>
            <p>Q 67. <hi>How often is Baptiſm to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to the ſame perſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Only once. 1. Becauſe it is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of our New Birth, and we are to be but once new born.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe it is the Ordinance of our Admiſſion or Entrance into the Church of O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſt, and we are to be entered but once into it.</p>
            <p>Q. 68. <hi>Which is the other Sacrament of the New Teſtament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The other Sacrament of the New Teſtament is the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. 69. <hi>What is the Lord's Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lord's Supper is an holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt, wherein by giving and receiving Bread and Wine, according to Chriſt's appointment, his Death is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth, and the worthy Receivers are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after a corporal and carnal manner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by Faith, made partakers of his Body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Blood, with all his Benefits to their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152928:16"/>Spiritual Nouriſhment and Growth in Grace, the confirming of their Union &amp; Communion with Chriſt, the teſtifying and renewing their Covenant with God, and thankfulneſs to him, and their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Love to, and fellowſhip with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Members of the ſame Myſtical Body, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.26, 27, 28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24, 25, 26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17.</p>
            <p>Q 70. <hi>What be the parts of the Lord</hi>'s <hi>Sapper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are two. The outward and viſible parts ſignifying; and the inward and ſpiritual part ſignified.</p>
            <p>Q. 71. <hi>What are the outward parts of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The outward parts of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance are three; (1) Signifying Things or Elements; (2.) Signifying Words; (3.) Signifying Affions.</p>
            <p>Q. 72. <hi>What are the ſignifying Things or Elements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>Q. 73. <hi>What do they ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Bread ſignifieth and repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Body of Chriſt. The Wine, the Blood of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Both together ſignifie whole <hi>Chriſt</hi> with all his Saving Benefits.</p>
            <p>Q. 74. <hi>What be the ſignifying Words?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152928:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The words of Inſtitution, <hi>Take, Eat, This is my Body which is broken for you,; Do this in remembrance of me:</hi> And, <hi>This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood, ſhed for many for the Remiſſion of Sins, Drink ye all of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. 75. <hi>What do theſe words ſignifie, or contain?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They contain, 1. A <hi>Command,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring the uſe of this Ordinance, in theſe words, <hi>Take, Eat, This Bread,</hi> and <hi>Drink of this Cup. Do this in remembrance of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Promiſe,</hi> aſſuring us of <hi>Chriſt</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelf to the worthy Receivers, in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and <hi>This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. 76. <hi>Are the Elements of Bread and Wine then turned into the very Body and Blood of Chriſt in this Ordinance after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. They remain ſtill in their own Nature, real Bread and Wine, and are only changed from a common to a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Uſe, to ſignifie and repreſent the Body and Blood of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. 77. <hi>How may this be proved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Three ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Scripture.</hi> Which informs us that the Body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was whole, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152928:17"/>his Blood in his Veins, when he firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and adminiſtred this Ordinance; &amp; that the ſame Body was afterward crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, buried, roſe again on the third day, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared alive to many Witneſſes, and at length aſcended into Heaven, &amp; that it is there to remain until the time of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all things, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.35. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.4, 5, 6. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. and 3.21. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 78. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. By <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For <hi>Chriſt</hi> having but one Body, it is againſt Reaſon to think that he could both give his Body to his Diſciples to eat, and his Blood to drink; and yet at the ſame time have it ſtill alive and whole by them. Had it been thus, he muſt have had two Bodies at the ſame time; for its contrary to the nature of a Body to be in two places at once.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea further;</hi> If the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine</hi> were turned into the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then ſuppoſing the Lord's Supper was adminiſtred in a thouſand places at the ſame time, <hi>Chriſt</hi> would have a thouſand <hi>Bodies</hi> at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>Q. 79. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. By <hi>Senſe.</hi> For we ſee and taſte that it is ſtill <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>VVine,</hi> and not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152928:18"/>Fleſh and <hi>Blood.</hi> And if we cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve our Senſes in this matter, How ſhall we believe them in any other thing?</p>
            <p>Q 80. <hi>But doth not Chriſt call the Bread his Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and the Wine his Blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes; but Chriſt ſpeaks this not in a proper, but in a figurative, or improper ſenſe, calling the ſign by the name of the thing ſignified by it; which manner of ſpeech Chriſt did often uſe: So he calls himſelf, a Door, a Vine, a Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not that he was really changed into theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things; but to teach us, that he is of like uſe to our Souls, that theſe are to our Bodies, <hi>John</hi> 10.7. and 15.1.</p>
            <p>Q. 81. <hi>Is not Chriſt then really and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent in this Ordinance of his Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes. Chriſt is really and truly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in this as in all other Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but not corporally or carnally, but ſpiritually; and ſo he is to be fed upon, not by the Mouth of the Body, but of the Soul, that is, to be received, &amp; applied to the Soul by Faith, <hi>John</hi> 6.56. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>Q. 82. <hi>What are the ſignifying Actions to be uſed in this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. The <hi>Actions</hi> to be uſed by the Miniſter, are <hi>Taking, Bleſſing, Breaking,</hi> &amp; <hi>Giving</hi> the Bread to the Communicants,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152928:18"/>and <hi>Taking, giving Thanks,</hi> and <hi>giving</hi> the Cup alſo to them. 2. The <hi>Actions</hi> of the Communicants are <hi>Taking</hi> and <hi>Partaking,</hi> or <hi>Eating</hi> the <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>Drinking</hi> the <hi>Wine, Matt.</hi> 26.26, 27, 28.</p>
            <p>Q. 83. <hi>What is ſignified by the Miniſters taking the Bread and Wine when he cometh to the Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſignifieth God the Fathers taking or chooſing, and deſigning Chriſt from all Eternity to be Man's Redeemer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1.</p>
            <p>Q. 84. <hi>What is ſignified by the Miniſters Bleſſing the Elements, or giving Thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſignifieth the ſetting of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from a common to an holy uſe, and is to be performed by declaring the words of Inſtitution, and by praying to God for a bleſſing on this Ordinance, ioyned with giving Thanks unto God for Jeſus Chriſt, and for all his benefits.</p>
            <p>Q 85. <hi>What is ſignified by the Breaking of the Bread?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It ſignifieth all the Sufferings of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially the breaking of his Body &amp; ſhedding of his Blood upon the Croſs.</p>
            <p>Q. 86. <hi>What is ſignified by the Miniſters giving the Bread and Wine to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſignifieth God the Fathers giving
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152928:19"/>Chriſt as a Saviour, and Chriſt's giving himſelf, with all his benefits, to true Believers, <hi>John</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 87. <hi>What is ſignified by the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants taking the Bread and Wine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſignifieth their thankful accepting and receiving of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be their Saviour with all his benefits, by Faith, <hi>John</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 88. <hi>What is ſignified by the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants eating the Bread, and drinking the Wine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſignifieth their applying of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with all his benefits, by Faith, unto their own Souls in particular; that each Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may believingly ſay of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, My Lord, and my God,</hi> John 20.28.</p>
            <p>Q. 89. <hi>For what holy Ends is the Lord's Supper to be uſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For ſuch holy Ends as theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the preſerving of the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his matchleſs Love in dying for Sinners; this Ordinance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a lively ſhewing forth of his Death <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Q 90. <hi>What other End?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 2. For the ſpiritual nouriſhing and ſtrengthning of the inward Man, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grace in the Heart; as Faith, Repentance Love, Hope, <hi>&amp;c</hi> For this Reaſon it ſeems
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152928:19"/>to be call'd, <hi>a Supper,</hi> being a ſpiritual Meal for Souls, in which <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf is our ſpiritual Food, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20.</p>
            <p>Q 91. <hi>What other End?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. For the fealing and confirming the New Covenant of Grace, or the New Teſtament: For as the laſt Will or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of a Man is confirmed, and comes in force by the Death of the Teſtator, or of him that made it; ſo the Death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (which is repreſented in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance) confirms the New Covenant, as being <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s laſt Will and Teſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p>Q. 93. <hi>For what other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. For the teſtifying of <hi>Believers</hi> thankfulneſs to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for his Love to them in dying for them. Therefore it is ſometimes call'd the Euchariſt, or the Thankſgiving; and the <hi>Cup</hi> is call'd the <hi>Cup</hi> of bleſſing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
            <p>Q 93. <hi>For what other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 5. For the ſtrengthning and increaſe of believers Union to, and communion with <hi>Chriſt</hi> and him crucified; and alſo with one another, as Fellow-Members of the ſame Myſtical Body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Church;</hi> for which cauſe it is alſo call'd the Communion, 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 10.16, 17.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152928:20"/>
            <p>Q. 94. <hi>Is it ſufficient to partake of the Lord's Supper (as of Baptiſm) only once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. <hi>Believers</hi> ſhould often partake of this Ordinance (if it may be) becauſe of their conſtant need of it, in order to the obtaining of the holy Ends thereof, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</p>
            <p>Q. 95. <hi>To whom is the Lord's Supper to be adminiſtred?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lord's Supper is to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred only to ſuch as have a Goſpel-right to it, and a Goſpel fitneſs, or prepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for it.</p>
            <p>Q. 96. <hi>What is a Goſpel-right to this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is a twofold Goſpel-right, (1.) Outward, with Reference to the Church; (2.) Inward, with Reference to God.</p>
            <p>Q. 97. <hi>Who have an outward Right, with Reference to the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch have an outward and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Right to the Lord's Supper, who being baptized and grown Perſons, do make a credible Profeſſion of their being in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, or of their Faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Obedience to him, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 37, 38.</p>
            <p>Q. 98. <hi>When is their Profeſſion to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted credible, or worthy to be believed?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152928:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When they have a competent mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Goſpel-knowledge, ſeriouſly and underſtandingly own and conſent to their Covenant with God in baptiſm, and live a religious and unblameable Life accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Goſpel-Rule, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.</p>
            <p>Q. 99. <hi>Who may examine and judge of this outward and viſible Right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That particular Church of Chriſt, with which they deſire to joyn, and walk in full Communion, eſpecially the Paſtor thereof, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</p>
            <p>Q. 100. <hi>Who then are to be kept off from this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch as are groſly ignorant of the Doctrine of Chriſt, or openly vicious and ſcandalous in their Lives.</p>
            <p>Q. 101. <hi>Who are to be accounted groſly ignorant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch as underſtand not the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Chriſtian Religion, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the New Birth, or a Work of Grace upon their Heart, nor the Nature, Uſe and Ends of this holy Ordinance, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.34.</p>
            <p>Q. 102. <hi>Why ſhould ſuch ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be kept off from this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they want an Eye to diſcern the Lord's Body, an hand to receive him,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152928:21"/>and a Mouth to feed upon him; and therefore if they ſhould partake of this Ordinance, they would receive no bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but much hurt by it.</p>
            <p>Q. 103. <hi>Who are to be accounted openly vicious, or ſcandalous?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch as live in any open or known courſe of ſin impenitently, and by their Words or Actions give juſt cauſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to thoſe that fear God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</p>
            <p>Q. 104. <hi>Why ſhould ſuch vicious perſons be kept off?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they, in preſuming to touch ſuch holy things with unholy hands and hearts, would diſhonour &amp; provoke God, pollute and profane his Ordinance, grieve the Godly, contract the guilt of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Blood,</hi> and eat and drink Judgment to themſelves, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27, 29. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.26.</p>
            <p>Q. 105. <hi>But may not the Lord</hi>'s <hi>Supper be adminiſtred to vicious perſons in order to their Converſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. For we do not find that Chriſt appointed this Ordinance to convert ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but to confirm and comfort Saints; it is not to work grace, where it is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but to increaſe and ſtrengthen grace where it is.</p>
            <p>Q. 106. <hi>Who have an inward inviſible Right to this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152928:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch who are indeed Heart-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters with God, or do believe in <hi>Chriſt</hi> with their hearts, and obey him in their lives.</p>
            <p>Q. 107. <hi>Who are Heart-covenanters with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe, who truly repent of their ſins againſt God, Renounce the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, and take God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt for their only God, and chief Good, their Father, Redeemer, and Sanctifier, and give up themſelves to fear, love and obey him, according to his Word, and this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Death, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.5. and 56.4.</p>
            <p>Q. 108. <hi>How may we know, that we are in Covenant with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We may know it by theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By our ſincere conſenting to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, or chooſing the living and true God to be our God, and giving up our ſelves to be his People.</p>
            <p>Q. 109. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. By our holy care to keep Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, and to perform the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which he requireth of us therein.</p>
            <p>Q. 110. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. By God's gracious performance
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152928:22"/>of the Promiſes of his Covenant to our Souls, in giving us the Saving Bleſſings promiſed to his Covenant-People.</p>
            <p>Q. 111. <hi>What are the Bleſſings which God hath promiſed in the Covenant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God hath promiſed grace and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, all that is needful and good, both temporal, ſpiritual, and eternal Bleſſings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>Q. 112. <hi>What he the Spiritual Bleſſings that God hath promiſed to them in this life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe eſpecially God hath promiſed to give them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Holy Spirit, to teach, ſanctifie, aſſiſt, guide, and comfort them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17, 26.</p>
            <p>Q. 113. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The enlightning of their Minds with Saving Knowledge, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.11.</p>
            <p>Q. 114. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The renewing of their Wills or Hearts, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. and 11.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Q. 115. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The putting of his Law in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Parts, and writing it in their hearts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10.</p>
            <p>Q. 116. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The putting his Fear in their hearts,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152928:22"/>to keep them from departing from him <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</p>
            <p>Q. 117. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Juſtification of their Perſons, pardoning their Sins, and Accepting them as Righteous in Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24, 25, 26.</p>
            <p>Q. 118. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Sanctification of their Natures, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25.</p>
            <p>Q. 119. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Adoption to be the Children of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18.</p>
            <p>Q. 120. <hi>How may we know whether we have the Spirit of God, or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We may know it by the Operations, Fruits, or Effects of the Spirit in us, which are ſuch as theſe, Light, Life, Love, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Repentance, Hope, Meekneſs and Temperance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. and 5.22, 23.</p>
            <p>Q. 121. <hi>How may we know whether we have a new Heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. By the uprightneſs, ſingleneſs, and ſenſibleneſs, or tenderneſs of our hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the Conformity of our Hearts to the Law of God, when it is the bent deſire,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152928:23"/>&amp; delight of our Hearts to do the Will of God, and pleaſe him in every thing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6, 8, 16. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8.</p>
            <p>Q. 122. <hi>Who muſt judge of this inward inviſible Right to the Lord's Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Every particular Chriſtian ought to examine and judge of his own inward and inviſible Right by the help of God's Spirit, and the Rule of his Word, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p>Q 123. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at is a Goſpel-fitneſs, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paredneſs for this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is a twofold Goſpel fitneſs for it. 1. A fitneſs of our State or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. 2. A fitneſs of our Frame or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Both theſe muſt be had to make us worthy Gueſs at this Holy Table of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Q. 124. <hi>Who are in a fit State or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch, and only ſuch as are in a ſtate of Saving Grace, or the Childern of God by Regeneration, and ſo qualified with thoſe Graces that are needful and uſeful for a right receiving of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and a ſpiritual profiting by it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p>Q. 125. <hi>What is Saving-Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Saving Grace is a Principle of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152928:23"/>Life wrought in the Hearts of God's Elect by the Holy Spirit, and (uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) by the Miniſtry of the Word, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are effectually inclined and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and do ſincerely endeavour to obey the whole revealed Will of God in Heart, Lip, and Life, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>John</hi> 17.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 126. <hi>How may we know that we have Saving-Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We may know it by the good Fruits and Effects of it, which are eſpecially theſe two:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Saving Grace turns the Heart from all ſin, and ſets it againſt ſin, ſo that ſuch a Man doth not only forbear ſin, but hates it, and ſeeks the utter deſtruction of it in his Heart and Life, by all good means. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.30. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.104. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saving Grace turns the Heart unto God and Godlineſs, ſtrongly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly inclines it to that which is good, and makes us fit and ready to, and active in good Works, enables us cheerfully to obey the Will of God's Precept, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to ſubmit to the Will of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152928:24"/>112. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>Q. 127. <hi>What are the particular Graces, or gracious Qualifications, that fits us for a worthy partaking of the Lord</hi>'s <hi>Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are eſpecially theſe ſeven; Knowledge, Faith, Repentance, Love, New Obedience, Thankfulneſs &amp; Holy Deſire, or a Spiritual Appetite to this Ordinance.</p>
            <p>128. <hi>What Knowledge ſhould we have?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A competent meaſure of Knowledge of the Fundamental or Principal Truths of the Chriſtian Religion, or of ſuch things as are revealed in the holy Scriptures, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make us wiſe unto Salvation, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9. &amp; 3.10.</p>
            <p>Q. 129. <hi>What are the Truths that we ſhould eſpecially know?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Some Truths concerning God, ſome concerning Man, ſome concerning the Covenant between God and Man, and ſome concerning the Sacraments, or Seals of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>Q 130. <hi>What ſhould we know concerning God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould know <hi>ſomething</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Eſſence or Nature, <hi>ſomething</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Will, and <hi>ſomething</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Q. 131. <hi>What ſhould we know concerning the Eſſence, or Nature of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152928:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God is, or that there is a God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</p>
            <p>Q. 132. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. That God is One; or that there is only One true God, and no more, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10.</p>
            <p>Q. 133. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That this One God ſubſiſteth in three diſtinct Perſons, called by diſtinct Names in Scripture, The Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, or Spirit, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p>Q. 134. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. That this One God is a moſt pure inviſible Spirit, or a Being that cannot be ſeen by our Eyes, <hi>John</hi> 4.24. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. and 6.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 135. <hi>By What hath God made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf known to us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God hath made himſelf known to us two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By his written Word. 2. By his Works.</p>
            <p>Q. 136. <hi>What doth the Word make known to us concerning the Nature of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Word makes known to us the Names, Titles, and Attributes of God, by which his Nature is in ſome meaſure diſcovered.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152928:25"/>
            <p>Q. 137. <hi>What are the Names or Titles of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is called <hi>Jehovah, Jah,</hi> and in Scripture, which ſignifieth his Eſſence, or Self-exiſtence; that he hath his Being in and of himſelf, and gives Being to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Beings. He is the Eternal, <hi>I am.</hi> He is called <hi>God Almighty, or All-ſufficient, The moſt High God, Poſſeſſor of Heaven and Earth, The Lord of Hosts, The God of Gods, The King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords.</hi> Theſe, and many other Titles are given to God in Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.3. and 34.6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. and 14.19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.27. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 138. <hi>What are the Attributes of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God's Attributes are certain Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, Perfections, or Excellencies in his Nature or Eſſence, whereby he is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from all other Beings.</p>
            <p>Q. 139. <hi>How are God's Attributes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed each from other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are diſtinguiſhed into two ſorts; his Abſolute, and his Relative Attributes.</p>
            <p>Q. 140. <hi>Which are God's Abſolute At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such as are only in God, and of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152928:25"/>which there is no Reſemblance in any Creatures.</p>
            <p>Q. 141. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His Simplicity, or Freedom from all Compoſition. He is a moſt abſolute, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and pure Spirit, without Body, Parts, or Paſſions, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15, 16. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.39.</p>
            <p>Q. 142. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His Infinity. God is infinite, that is, without Bounds of Place, Time or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. He is in all places at once, &amp; yet not comprehended in any place. He was before all Time, is in all Time, and will be when Time ſhall be no more. And ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that he cannot be more perfect, in all Excellencies. And therefore no Man nor Angel can fully underſtand and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what God is, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.23. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7. &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.2. and 145.3. <hi>Job</hi> 11.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>Q. 143. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His All-ſufficiency. God is ſufficient or himſelf, and for all his Creatures; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt needs be ſo, ſeeing he is infinite in Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs, &amp; in all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ections, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. &amp; 12.9.</p>
            <p>Q. 144. <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His Independency. God hath no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ependence on any other Being, but all
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152928:26"/>other Beings have their whole dependence on him, both for Subſiſtence, Supplies, Powers, and Actions, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.25. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</p>
            <p>Q. 145. <hi>Which is the fifth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His Immutability, or Unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs. God is always the ſame, and ſubject to no Change, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.</p>
            <p>Q. 146. <hi>Which are God's Relative At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such, of which there is ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance in the reaſonable Creatures, Angels and Men.</p>
            <p>Q. 147. <hi>Which be they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. <hi>His Life.</hi> He is the Living God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.2.</p>
            <p>Q. 148. <hi>Which is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. <hi>His Will.</hi> He worketh all things according to the Councel of his Will <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            <p>Q. 149. <hi>Which another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. <hi>His Wiſdom and Knowledge.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the only wiſe God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</p>
            <p>Q. 150. <hi>Which is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. <hi>His Power.</hi> Which ſignifie both. 1. <hi>His Authority,</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all his Creatures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.19. <hi>Dan.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 34, 35. <hi>Jude v.</hi> 25.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152928:26"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>His Strength or Might.</hi> He can do what ever he will, <hi>Job</hi> 42.1, 2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.26.</p>
            <p>Q. 151. <hi>Which is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 5. <hi>His Holineſs.</hi> He is moſt holy and pure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.3.</p>
            <p>Q. 152. <hi>Which is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 6. <hi>His Juſtice.</hi> He is moſt Juſt and Righteous, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.7. and 92.15.</p>
            <p>Q. 153. <hi>Which is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 7. <hi>His Goodneſs.</hi> He is moſt good. This comprehends both, 1. The <hi>Love,</hi> 2. The <hi>Graciouſneſs,</hi> 3. The <hi>Mercy,</hi> 4. The <hi>Patience of God, Pſal.</hi> 119.68. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8. and 145.8.</p>
            <p>Q. 154. <hi>Which is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 8. <hi>His Truth and Faithfulneſs,</hi> He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s moſt true, both in Himſelf, his Word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Works, <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. <hi>John</hi> 17.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.4.</p>
            <p>Q. 155. <hi>Are theſe Relative Attributes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n God, as they are in Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. <hi>In God</hi> they are his very Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, or Nature; for whatever is in God, is God. But in Man they are Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. In God they are moſt perfect; he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo merciful and juſt, that he cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore ſo. But in Man they are imperfect.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152928:27"/>are but ſome degrees of Mercy and Juſtice in him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>Q. 156. <hi>What are the Works of God whereby he makes himſelfe known?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are either, 1. <hi>His Works</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time, call'd his Decrees, whereby he purpoſed in himſelf from all Eternity what he would do in time. 2. <hi>His Work in time,</hi> which are the Executions, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Performances of his Decrees; which comprehend both his Works of Creation and his Works of Providence, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11 <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. and 1.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.19.</p>
            <p>Q. 157. <hi>What may we learn of God b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the Works of God we may lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſomewhat of the glorious Perfections <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Nature, his Wiſdom, Power, Holine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Juſtice, Goodneſs, and Truth; but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Holy Word diſcovers them more clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully to us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.2</p>
            <p>Q. 158. <hi>What is a Perſon in the Divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Perſon in the Divine Nature is diſtinct Subſiſtence, or Being, having t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whole Nature of God, but diſtinguiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> each from other by their order, incon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> municable Properties, and manner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> working, <hi>John</hi> 14.9, 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152928:27"/>
            <p>Q. 159. <hi>What is the Order of the Holy Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God the Father is the firſt Perſon, God the Son is the ſecond Perſon, and God the Holy Ghoſt is the third Perſon.</p>
            <p>Q. 160. <hi>What are their incommunicable Properties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the Property of the Father to beget the Son, the Property of the Son to be begotten of the Father, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the Spirit to proceed from the Father &amp; the Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. and 15.26.</p>
            <p>Q. 161. <hi>What is their manner of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God the Father worketh from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; God the Son worketh from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; God the Holy Ghoſt worketh both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom the Father and the Son, <hi>John</hi> 5.26.</p>
            <p>Q. 162. <hi>VVhat ſhould we know concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt Perſon in the Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Four things eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he is called God the Father, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe he is the Father of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Chriſt by an inconceivable Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n; and becauſe he is the Father of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Beings by Creation, <hi>John</hi> 20.17. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</p>
            <p>Q. 163. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. That he created all things in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152928:28"/>beginning of time, and having made man after his own Image, he covenanted or promiſed to continue him in his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, provided man continued in his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27, 31. and 2.16, 17.</p>
            <p>Q. 164. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. That Man breaking that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by his Diſobedience, and ſo making himſelf liable to Death, it pleaſed God to pitty his fall'n and ſinful Creature, &amp; to contrive a way of Salvation for him, by virtue of a ſecond Covenant in and through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>John</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 165. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. That God the Father firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, &amp; in the fulneſs of time ſent forth his only begotten Son the Lord Jeſus, Chriſt into the World, to be Man's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and Saviour, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. &amp; 12.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.7. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>Q. 166. <hi>VVhat ſhould we know concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond Perſon in the Holy Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe four things eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he freely undertook this great Work of Man's Redemption, &amp; engaged himſelf by Covenant to God the Father for the faithful performance of it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 42.6, 7. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 40.7.8.</p>
            <p>Q. 167. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152928:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. That in order to the performing of this Work, he took our Nature into Union with his Divine Nature, &amp; ſo was and is both God and Man in one Perſon, <hi>John</hi> 1.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p>Q. 168. <hi>VVas it needful that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer ſhould be Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Yes, becauſe Man had ſinned, &amp; ſo it was juſt that the Nature which had ſinn'd ſhould ſuffer, &amp; ſatisfie for Sin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>Q. 169. <hi>VVas it needful that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer ſhould be God alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. Becauſe he could not elſe have been able to undergo the Wrath of God, due to us for ſin; nor would his Sufferings have been of ſufficient value and virtue to procure Salvation for us.</p>
            <p>Q 170. <hi>VVhat elſe ſhould we know of this ſecond Perſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. That he, as our Redeemer, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the Offices of a Prophet, Prieſt, &amp; King, to deliver ſinful Men from their Ignorances, Sin and Slavery, &amp; to bring them to compleat and eternal Salvation, <hi>Acts.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6.</p>
            <p>Q. 171. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. That he procureth by his Blood and Merit many precious Benefits for his Redeemed ones; to be enjoyed, ſome in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152928:29"/>this World, and others in the World to come, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p>Q. 172. <hi>What are thoſe Benefits or Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Principal Benefits procured by Chriſt for his Redeemed Ones, are Juſtification, Adoption, and Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with many others, that do either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company or flow from them, or certainly follow them, ſufficient Grace on Earth, and eternal Glory in Heaven, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2, 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>Q. 173. <hi>What ſhould we know concerning the third Perſon in the Holy Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe four things eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he inſpired all the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, revealed God's Mind and Will to them, and by them to the Church, and aſſiſted all the Penmen of the Holy Scriptures in Writing them, both as to Matter and Words, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p>Q. 174. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 2. That he was firſt promiſed by Chriſt, and after his Aſcenſion, ſent both by the Father and the Son, to ſupply the Churches ſpiritual Wants in Chriſt's bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Abſence from it, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17. and 16.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152928:29"/>
            <p>175. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 3. That he doth bleſs the Word &amp; Ordinances of Chriſt, and make them ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Means of Grace to the Elect, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith in them, &amp; thereby uniting 'em to Chriſt in their effectual Calling, &amp; ſo applies to them the Redemption purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt, with all the Saving Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his Mediatorſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</p>
            <p>Q 176. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 4. That he doth dwell in all that are effectually called &amp; drawn to Jeſus Chriſt, leading, quickning, &amp; comforting them, and carrying on the Work of Grace and Sanctification unto Perfection, to prepare them for Glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.11, 13, 14, 15, 16, <hi>John</hi> 14.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 177. <hi>What ſhould we know concerning the VVill of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould know that God hath fully revealed his Holy Mind and Will to us in the Scriptures of the Old &amp; New Teſtament to be the only perfect &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Rule of our Faith and Obedience, which therefore we ought to know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and obey in order to the pleaſing and glorifying of God, and the ſaving of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152928:30"/>our own Souls, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6 16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2.46. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32.</p>
            <p>Q. 178. <hi>VVhat ſhould we know concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the VVorſhip of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould know that this one God is to be worſhipped and ſerved by us both publickly, in the Church, privately, in our Families, &amp; ſecretly, in our Cloſets. And that his Worſhip is to be performed from a right Principle, Grace in our Hearts, by a right Rule, the written Word of God, to a right End, the Glory of God in our Salvation, and through the Mediator Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. &amp; 6.6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 26.2. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.14, 15. <hi>John</hi> 4.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15.</p>
            <p>Q. 179. <hi>VVhat ſhould we know concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His four-fold Eſtate, <hi>(viz.)</hi> 1. His good Eſtate by Creation. 2. His evil Eſtate by Tranſgreſſion. 3. His Holy Eſtate by Regeneration. 4. His happy Eſtate by Glorification.</p>
            <p>Q. 180. <hi>VVhat was Man's Eſtate by Creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Man was created after the Image of God in Knowledge, Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, had Dominion over all the Creatures in this lower World, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152928:30"/>many other Priviledges and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which made his Condition truely happy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.15. &amp; 8.4, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. 181. <hi>VVere all Mankind concerned in the ſtate of</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. <hi>Adam</hi> being a publick Perſon, the general Parent, or Root of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the Bleſſings beſtowed on him were alſo beſtowed on them, as being his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and then in his Loins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.9, 10.</p>
            <p>Q. 182. <hi>VVhat is Man's Eſtate by Tranſgreſſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Man by tranſgreſſing the Command of God in Eating the forbidden Fruit, loſt the Image of God, &amp; all the Priviledges and Bleſſings of the ſtate of Innocency, &amp; brought himſelf into a guilty, filthy, and accurſed ſtate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9, 10, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>Q. 183. <hi>Are all Mankind concerned in this ſtate of</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. All Mankind being in <hi>Adam</hi>'s Loins, and under the ſame Covenant with him, ſinned againſt God in him, and ſo fell with him in his firſt Tranſgreſſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Q 184 <hi>VVhat is Man's Eſtate by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152928:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Man by Regeneration is recovered out of his ſinful and miſerable ſtate into a ſtate of Grace and Mercy, hath the Image of God renewed upon him, is brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Covenant of Grace, &amp; hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a right to all the Priviledges and Bleſſings of the Children of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.17, 18. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>Q 185. <hi>Are all Mankind brought into this ſtate of Regeneration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. Only thoſe are brought into this eſtate that are choſen of God from all Eternity, &amp; given to Jeſus Chriſt, as to their Redeemer and Saviour, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4, 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>John</hi> 6.37.</p>
            <p>Q. 186. <hi>VVhat ſhall Man's Eſtate by Glorification be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Man ſhall be made perfectly Holy and Happy both in Soul and Body, in the full Enjoyment of God in Heaven, &amp; that to all Eternity, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>Q. 187. <hi>Shall all Mankind be brought into this ſtate of Glorification?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. Only thoſe that are made truly gracious here, ſhall be made glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hereafter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.46. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152928:31"/>
            <p>Q. 188. <hi>What ſhould we know concerning the Covenants between God and Man, &amp; the Sacraments or Seals of the Covenants?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould have a competent Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Divine Inſtitution, Spiritual Nature, holy uſe and ends of them. [But theſe things have been already opened.] Thus much of Knowledge.</p>
            <p>Q 189. <hi>What is that Faith which a worthy Partaker of the Lord's Supper ſhould have?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Saving Faith in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. 190. <hi>What is a Saving Faith in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Saving Faith in Chriſt is a ſpecial Gift of God to his Elect, whereby they knowing and aſſenting to the Truth of God's Record touching Chriſt in the Word, do Receive the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for their only Saviour, and truſt in him for Salvation on his own Terms, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. <hi>John</hi> 17.3 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10, 11. <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23.</p>
            <p>Q. 191. <hi>Why is Faith needful to a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Faith muſt be the Eye of the Soul to ſee Chriſt in it, the Hand of the Soul to Receive, the Spiritual Mouth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152928:32"/>and Stomach to feed upon him and digeſt him, as our Spiritual Food, for our Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and Growth in Grace.</p>
            <p>Q. 192. <hi>What is that Repentance a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Partaker ſhould have?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> True Repentance is a ſpecial Gift of God to his Elect, ariſing from a clear ſight and deep ſenſe of ſin, and a knowledge and belief of the Mercy of God in Chriſt, whereby they do both confeſs their ſins to God, with ſhame, and ſorrow for them, and hatred of them, and turn from them unto God, both in Heart and Life, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.11. &amp; 5.31. &amp; 2.37. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 26. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12, 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.104.</p>
            <p>Q. 193. <hi>Why is Repentance needful to a worthy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe in this Ordinance we come to renew our Covenant with God, and to receive a ſealed Pardon of our ſins, which none can do but true Penitents.</p>
            <p>Q. 194. <hi>VVhat is that Love a worthy Partaker ſhould have?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Holy Love is a Spiritual Affection whereby the Souls of God's People are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out toward God, and toward one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and toward all that is good, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.37.39. <hi>John</hi> 13.34. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.15. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.30. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152928:32"/>
            <p>Q. 195. <hi>Ought we not alſo to Love our very Enemies, and ſuch as hate us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. Chriſt hath commanded us to Love our Enemies with a Love of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, ſo as to forbear revenging our ſelves on them, and to deſire and endeavour their good, though not with a Love of Delight, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44, 45. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Q. 196. <hi>VVhy is love needful to a worthy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe this Ordinance is a Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feaſt, and a Love token between Chriſt &amp; his Church, in which they do as it were ſeal their Affections each to other, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to keep in memory Chriſt's Love to Believers, and to encreaſe their Love to him; and the want of this Love brings Men under the ſevereſt Curſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</p>
            <p>Q. 197. <hi>VVhat is that New Obedience that is needful to a worthy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> New Obedience is an unfeigned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and purpoſe of the Soul, ſeconded with a careful endeavour of Life (in and by the grace and ſtrength of Chriſt) to yeild ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere, conſtant, &amp; univerſal Obedience to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he whole revealed Mind &amp; Will of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yned with an humiliation for our Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152928:33"/>and Defects, a deſire to be found in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God only in, for &amp; through the perfect Obedience of Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.5, 8, 30, 31, 32. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6, 104, 112. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18, 19. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p>Q. 198. <hi>Why is it called New Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe 'tis only perform'd by New Creatures, that is, by ſuch as are renewed after the Image of God, and by new ſtrength from Chriſt; and becauſe it is required by the New Teſtament or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13.</p>
            <p>Q. 199. <hi>Why is this New Obedience need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to a worthy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe this Ordinance, being a Seal of the New Covenant, binds us to this New Obedience, ſo that without it our partaking of this Ordinance would be but diſſembling; and becauſe without this Obedience all our Profeſſion of Religion and outward Performances, will be reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God as vain and hypo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritical and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11.19, 23. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Q. 200. <hi>What is that Thankfulneſs that is needful to a worthy partaking of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152928:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thankfulneſs is a due and heart-affecting ſenſe of the Love of God in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt to us, of the Love of Chriſt in giving himſelf for us, and of the Love of the Spirit in revealing Chriſt in us, with a cheerful acknowledgment of the ſame with our Lips and Lives, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17.</p>
            <p>Q. 201. <hi>What ſhould Believers be eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thankful for at this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They ſhould be eſpecially thankful for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and for the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, together with all the Bleſſings and Benefits given in and with them to Believers, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p>Q. 202. <hi>Why is this Thankfulneſs need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to a worthy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt himſelf gave Thanks to God in the Inſtitution of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and becauſe the very matter, uſe, and ends of this Ordinance engaged us to Thankfulneſs, in that it repreſenteth, ſealeth, and applieth Jeſus Chriſt to us as the Spiritual Food of our Souls, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.10. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.18.</p>
            <p>Q 203. <hi>What is that holy Deſire, or ſpiritual Appetite that is needful to a worthy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152928:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Holy Deſire is a ſpiritual hungering and thirſting after the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as the Food of our Souls for our Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Growth in Grace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.8, 9. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6.</p>
            <p>Q. 204. <hi>Why is this holy Deſire or Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite needful to a worthy partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe this Ordinance (being a Spiritual Feaſt or Supper) cannot profit us without a ſpiritual hunger or thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Proviſions ſet before us therein; neither ſhall we taſte any ſpiritual ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in it, nor get Refreſhment and Nouriſhment by it; for this is promiſed only to thoſe who have this Appetite. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.52.</p>
            <p>Q. 205. <hi>Who are in a fit frame or diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such who being truly gracious, have ſome Scripture-Evidence thereof, and have got their Souls into a ſerious, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and holy diſpoſition to draw near to God, and to hold Communion with him, <hi>James</hi> 4.8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Q. 206. <hi>How may we get into a new frame or diſpoſition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We may get into a ſit frame or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition of Spirit for this holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152928:34"/>1. By examining our ſelves. 2. By quickning and ſtirring up our Graces. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> praying for Spiritual Bleſſings. 4. By hoping for them, and expecting of them from God through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. 207. <hi>Concerning what ſhould we exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould examine our ſelves, both concerning our Sins, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Graces, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5, 28.</p>
            <p>Q. 208. <hi>What ſhould we examine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Sins?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould examine both what our Sins are, and how they are aggravated by their ſeveral Circumſtances? <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6.</p>
            <p>Q 209. <hi>How may we come to know our Sins?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We may come to know our Sins,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By comparing our Hearts and Lives with the Laws of God, which ſhew us both the Duties we ſhould perform, and the ſins we ſhould avoid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. &amp; 7.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By praying to God to diſcover our ſins to us, <hi>Job</hi> 13.23.</p>
            <p>Q 210. <hi>What ſhould we examine our ſelves concerning our Graces?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould examine our ſelves, both touching the Grace we have, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152928:35"/>touching the Grace we want, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p>Q. 211. <hi>What ſhould we examine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Grace we have?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould examine both the truth of our Grace, and the growth of it.</p>
            <p>Q. 212. <hi>How may we know whether our knowledge of ſpiritual Truths, be a true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the Properties, Effects, and Companions of it in the Soul.</p>
            <p>Q. 213. <hi>What be the Properties of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is joyned with an high prizing of this knowledge it ſelf, and the things that we know, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 214. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is joyned with an humbling ſenſe of our own Ignorance and Sinfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs, <hi>Job</hi> 42.5, 6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.2.</p>
            <p>Q. 215. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is joyned with a Love to, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Spiritual Truths known, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.97. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22.</p>
            <p>Q. 216. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is accompanied with earneſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and diligent Endeavours after more Spiritual Knowledge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.33, 34, 40. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.3, 4. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>Q. 217. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:152928:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is accompanied with an Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or ſpiritual Senſe of thoſe Truths that are to be experienced; as of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing. converting, comforting, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and confirming power of the Word and Spirit of God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7, 8. &amp; 119.50. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32.</p>
            <p>Q. 218. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It changeth the Soul into the ſame Image of Holineſs that is in the Word of God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2.</p>
            <p>Q. 219. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is joyned with the practiſe of known Duties, and the forbearing of known ſins, <hi>John</hi> 13.17. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.3, 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.100, 101.</p>
            <p>Q. 220. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is joyned with a readineſs to teach others the knowledge of ſpiritual things, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.11. <hi>John</hi> 1.41, 45, 46. <hi>John</hi> 4.28, 29.</p>
            <p>Q 221. <hi>How may we know whether our Faith be true and ſaving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the manner in which it is wrought, by its nature, and by its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties or effects.</p>
            <p>Q 222. <hi>How is Faith wrought in the Soul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of God ordinarily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152928:36"/>the Heart for it by the Law of God, and then worketh it by the Goſpel?</p>
            <p>Q. 223. <hi>How doth the Spirit prepare the heart for Faith by the Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe ſeveral ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſhews and convinces the Soul of its ſinful and miſerable Eſtate by nature, <hi>John</hi> 16.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It humbles the Soul under the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration of its ſin and miſery, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It works in the Soul a deſpair of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of this condition, by its own power, or the help of any other Creatures, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It cauſeth in the Soul a fear of the wrath of God, due to him for ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It convinceth the Soul of its need of a Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 224. <hi>How doth the Spirit of God work Faith by the Goſpel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe ſeveral ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſhews to the Soul the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as an All-ſufficient and only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, provided by God, and offered to ſinners, <hi>John</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It begets in the Soul an high eſteem of this Saviour, and earneſt deſires after him, above all other things, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152928:36"/>
            <p n="3">3. It convinceth the Soul that it is his duty to believe in, or cloſe with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for his Saviour, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It begets in the ſoul ſome hope of obtaining an Intereſt in this Saviour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.116.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It works in the Soul a Reſolution to ſeek after this Saviour, and to be at any care and coſt to obtain an intereſt in him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It takes the Soul wholly off from reſting on his own Righteouſneſs for Juſtification before God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p>Q. 225. <hi>Wherein doth the Eſſence or Nature of Faith conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It conſiſts in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In a receiving of an whole Chriſt, or of Chriſt in all his Offices; the Soul being made willing to be taught and ruled, as well as reconciled by him, <hi>John</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſting on Chriſt, or truſting in him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for compleat and eternal Salvation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p>Q. 226. <hi>What be the Properties, Fruits, or Effects of Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith helps to ſoften and melt the heart into godly ſorrow for ſin, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5, 6.</p>
            <p>Q. 227. <hi>What is another property of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152928:37"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith helps to purifie or cleanſe the Heart from the love of ſin, by arguing againſt it from the Word of God, and by applying the Blood of Chriſt to the Soul, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. <hi>John</hi> 17.17. <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1.</p>
            <p>Q. 228. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith makes a Man obedient to the Will of God, and fruitful in good Works, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8, 9, 17.</p>
            <p>Q. 229. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith maintains the Chriſtian's ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Life, as it applies Chriſt and the Promiſes to the ſoul, and helps the ſoul to live in an holy dependance upon him and them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p>Q. 230. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith makes the Word of God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and effectual to the Soul, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2:13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2.</p>
            <p>Q. 231. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith helps the Soul to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> nigh to God in holy Duties, with hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oldneſs and confidence of acceſs to him, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with him through Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. &amp; 10.22.</p>
            <p>Q. 232. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith helps the Soul to bear the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Troubles and Afflictions, and keep it from fainting and ſinking under them,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152928:37"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. <hi>Job</hi> 13.15.</p>
            <p>Q. 233. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith helps the Soul to reſiſt and conquer its ſpiritual Enemies, Sin, Satan, and the World, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.16. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.24.25, 26.</p>
            <p>Q. 234. <hi>VVhat is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith helps the Soul to ſpiritual Joy and Peace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2 and 15.13.</p>
            <p>Q. 235. <hi>What is another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith is of a growing and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Nature, encreaſeth in Meaſure, and endures to the end, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1 3 <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.39. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination of Repentance.</head>
               <p>Q. 236. <hi>How may we know whether our Repentance be true and ſaving?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the manner of its working, by its Nature, and by its Fruits, Effects, and Companions.</p>
               <p>Q. 237. <hi>In what manner is Repentance wrought?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of God ordinarily work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a ſight and ſenſe of ſin in the Soul by the Law, and an apprehenſion of the Mercy of God in Chriſt offered to ſinners by the Goſpel, and herewith powerfully
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152928:38"/>affects the Heart, and effectually inclines it to turn from ſin unto God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. &amp; 7.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. &amp; 26.18. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18.</p>
               <p>Q. 238. <hi>Wherein doth the Nature of true Repentance conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In theſe three things: 1. In a deep Conviction of ſin. 2. In an hearty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, or godly Sorrow for ſin. 3. In a thorow Converſion or Turning from ſin to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.30.</p>
               <p>Q. 239. <hi>When is our Conviction of ſin ſuch as it ought to be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we underſtand and are duly ſenſible of the greatneſs of the Evil of ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.9.</p>
               <p>Q. 240. <hi>Wherein doth the evil of ſin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. In its odious Nature, as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary both to the Holy Nature Revealed Will, and Righteous Law of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In its hurtful Fruits and Effects, as bringing the Soul under guilt, filth, and ſlavery, and making it liable to temporal, ſpiritual, and eternal Puniſhments, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Job</hi> 15.16. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</p>
               <p>Q. 241. <hi>When is our Contrition or Sorrow for ſin ſuch as it ought to be?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:152928:38"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. When it is a ſorrow for ſin, as ſin, or as it is contrary to the Nature and Will of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When it is univerſal ſorrow for all ſins, &amp; at all times, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.18. &amp; 119.136.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When it is the greateſt ſorrow we have, both as to degree and continuance, <hi>Zech</hi> 12.10.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When it worketh repentance or forſaking of ſin, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.</p>
               <p>Q. 242. <hi>When is our Converſion from ſin unto God ſuch as it ought to be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we are turned from all ſin unto God, both in heart and life, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</p>
               <p>Q. 243. <hi>When is the heart turned from ſin to God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the Heart is turned from the Darkneſs of ſin to the light of Grace, or from ignorance to knowledge in the things of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When the Heart is turned from a Death in Sin to the Life of Grace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When the Heart is turned from the love of ſin to the hatred of it, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.104.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When the Heart is turned from the reigning power of ſin, and brought under the Government of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17, 18.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:152928:39"/>
               <p>Q. 244. <hi>When is the life turned from ſin unto God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we do in our practices and courſe of life, deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>Q. 245. <hi>What are the Fruits and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of true Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A free and full Confeſſion of ſin, with its aggravation unto God, and alſo unto Men, when duly called to it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>James</hi> 5.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Judging and Condemning ſin, and our ſelves for ſin, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.7, 8.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Loathing of ſin, and of our ſelves for ſin, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.43.</p>
               <p n="4">4. An holy ſhame upon the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſin, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.61.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A juſt Indignation againſt, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Revenge upon ſin in mortifying of it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Making Reſtitution or Satisfaction for ſin (though not to God, yet) to Men, (if it be in our power) for the wrong we have done to them, either in Souls or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Eſtates, or good Names, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8.</p>
               <p n="7">7. An holy deſire and carefulneſs to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſin, and pleaſe God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:152928:39"/>
               <p n="8">8. A holy Fear and Watchfulneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin and temptations for time to come, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination of Love.</head>
               <p>Q. 246. <hi>How may we know whether our Love to God the Father, Son &amp; Spirit be true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Riſe or Grounds of it, by the Nature of it, and by the Properties of it.</p>
               <p>Q. 247. <hi>Whence doth our Love to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. From a fight or diſcovery of the Lovelineſs of God, or the ſurpaſſing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of his Nature, apprehended by Faith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.1. &amp; 45.2. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From a Taſte or Experience of the Goodneſs and Mercy of God, and Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations of his Love to our Souls, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3. &amp; 3, 4, 5. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38.</p>
               <p>Q. 248. <hi>Wherein doth the Nature of this Love of God conſist?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the Soul's going out toward God as the chief Good, by ſeveral ſteps or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. As, 1. In a Love of Good-will to him. 2. In a Love of fervent Deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. 3. In a Love of ſweet Delight and full Satisfaction in him, <hi>John</hi> 3.27. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. &amp; 8.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5, 6.</p>
               <p>Q. 249. <hi>How may we know that we love God the Father as our Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:152928:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By our deſires and endeavours to carry it toward him like dutiful Children, fearing to offend him, hearkning to him, obeying him, ſeeking to him, and depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on him for all needful Bleſſings, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14, 15. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7.</p>
               <p>Q. 250. <hi>How may we know that we love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as our Mediator and Redeemer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By our renouncing all other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators and Redeemers, and thankfully accepting of him in all his Offices, as our only Mediator and Redeemer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By our learning of him as our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, obeying him as our King, uſing of him, and truſting in him as our Prieſt, for the Benefits of his Satisfaction and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. &amp; 4.15, 16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p>Q. 251. <hi>How may we know our Love to the Holy Spirit as our Sanctifier, Guide, and Comforter?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By our love to, frequenting of and delighting in the holy Ordinances of Chriſt by which the Spirit works, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 27.4. &amp; 81.1, 2, 10. &amp; 122.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By our hearkning to, and obeying his Call, cheriſhing his holy Motions in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152928:40"/>our Souls by the Ordinances of Chriſt, &amp; reſiſting and rejecting the evil ſuggeſtion and temptations of our ſpiritual Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By our ſetting upon Duties in the ſtrength of the Spirit, living under his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and walking in God's holy ways under his guidance, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.</p>
               <p>Q. 252. <hi>What are the properties of Love to God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a moſt hearty and fervent Love, exceeding our Love to all our Friends, Relations, Enjoyments, yea to our very Lives themſelves, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.27. &amp; 14.26, <hi>&amp;c. Acts</hi> 21.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6.</p>
               <p>Q. 253. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is an obedient Love, or makes the Soul obedient to the Will of God, and of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 14.15, 21. &amp; 15.10, 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.3.</p>
               <p>Q. 254. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It makes the Soul deſirous of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God, Communion with him, and of gracious Communications of Love and Mercy from him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1, 15. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17.15. &amp; 42.1, 2. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2.</p>
               <p>Q. 255. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:152928:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It helps the Soul patiently and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively to bear God's Rebukes and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, <hi>John</hi> 21.15, 16, 17. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.9.</p>
               <p>Q. 256. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is an abiding and conſtant Love, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.24. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6, 7.</p>
               <p>Q. 257. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It cauſes the Soul to love what God loves, becauſe he loves it, and hate what he hates, becauſe he hates it; and to grieve for the diſhonours done to him by our ſelves, or others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.5, 7. &amp; 146.8. &amp; 87.2. &amp; 26.8. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.14. &amp; 97.10. &amp; 139.21, 22.</p>
               <p>Q. 258. <hi>How may we know whether our love to other Chriſtians be true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By its Grounds or Cauſes, and by its Properties and Effects.</p>
               <p>Q. 259. <hi>What be the Grounds or Cauſes of Love to other Chriſtians?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Command of God and Chriſt requiring it, <hi>John</hi> 13.34. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our Love to God and Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining us to it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their Relation unto God as his Children, and to Chriſt as his Members, and to us as our Brethren and Fellow Members. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.25.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:152928:41"/>
               <p n="4">4. Their likeneſs to God and Chriſt in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Our Communion with them, and ſpiritual Benefits by them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.25</p>
               <p>Q. 260. <hi>What are the properties of this Love?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is Spiritual. A Love that flows from ſpiritual Cauſes, as when we love Chriſtians for God's ſake, for Chriſts ſake, and for Graces ſake, and aims at ſpiritual Ends, the Glory of God, and our mutual Good and Comfort, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.</p>
               <p>Q. 261. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is Univerſal. To all Chriſtians, as ſuch, whether high or low, rich or poor, bond or free, male or female, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14.</p>
               <p>Q. 262. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is ſtrong and Fervent, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <p>Q 263. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is Sociable, or makes us deſire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, frequent and delight in ſpiritual So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety with other Chriſtians, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.63. and 16.3.</p>
               <p>Q. 264. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is active and laborious, for the good of other Chriſtians, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.18.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:152928:42"/>
               <p>Q. 265. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is ſelf-denying, Condeſcending and Humble, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16. <hi>John</hi> 13.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</p>
               <p>Q. 266. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is ſympathizing, or a fellow-feeling affection, making us ſenſible both of the Joys and Sorrows of other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26.</p>
               <p>Q. 267. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is Patience in bearing Wrongs and Injuries from others, long ſuffering, ſlow to anger, and not eaſily provoked, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4, 7. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>Q. 268. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is Kind, Courteous and Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate both in Words and Actions, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us to relieve the Wants of others Souls and Bodies, according to our Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and their Neceſſity; to forbear reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves for wrongs, and to forgive them, and be reconciled, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4, 5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.10, 17, 18, 19 20. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.36. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</p>
               <p>Q. 269 <hi>But if another do me wrong, am I bound to forgive, and be reconciled to him, though he make me not ſatisfaction, profeſs repentance, nor ſeek reconcilation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. You are bound ſo far to forgive
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152928:42"/>him as to cheriſh no wrath, malice, deſire, or purpoſe of revenge againſt him; for theſe are ſins, and all ſins not repented of, unfit you for this holy Ordinance, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You are not bound to teſtifie your forgiving him, until he profeſs his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of the wrong done to you; but then you muſt do it, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You are not bound to receive him again into your familiar converſe, till he hath made ſatisfaction for the wrong done, or declared a purpoſe to do ſo, (if he be able) if not, at leaſt till he profeſs a willingneſs to do ſo, and a deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8.</p>
               <p>Q. 270. <hi>Which Party then is to keep off from the Lord's Supper, in caſe of wrong done, till they are reconciled?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Party that hath done the wrong only, not he that hath ſuffered wrong; for that would be to puniſh the Innocent, for the Offence of the Guilty, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.23.24.</p>
               <p>Q. 271. <hi>What is another property of this Love?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It envieth not at the proſperity, or better condition of others, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4.</p>
               <p>Q. 272. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It rejoyceth not in Iniquity, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in the Truth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.6.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:152928:43"/>
               <p>Q. 273. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a conſtant &amp; continuing Love, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Ruth.</hi> 1.16.17.</p>
               <p>Q. 274. <hi>How may we know whether our Love to our Enemies be true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Ground or Reaſon of it, and by the Fruits of it.</p>
               <p>Q. 275. <hi>What is the Reaſon of Love to our Enemies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. The Will of God made known to us in his Word, <hi>Matth</hi> 5.44. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The example of God in loving and forgiving us who were his Enemies, and the example of Chriſt in loving and dying for us, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.10.</p>
               <p>Q. 276. <hi>What are the Fruits of this Love?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. It makes us to will and deſire their good, <hi>Prov,</hi> 11.23.</p>
               <p>Q. 277. <hi>What is another Fruit of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. It keeps us from revenging our ſelves upon them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.17, 19.</p>
               <p>Q. 278. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 3. It inclines us to forgive them the Injuries done to us.</p>
               <p>Q. 279. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 4. It helps us to return good to them for their evil done to us, by praying for them, and relieving of their wants,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152928:43"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20, 21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.12, 13, 14. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.60. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.34.</p>
               <p>Q. 280. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 5 It keeps us from rejoycing in their hunt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.17, 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination of Obedience.</head>
               <p>Q. 281. <hi>How may we know whether our Obedience be true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Reaſons, the Principles, the Properties, the Rules, and the Ends of it.</p>
               <p>Q. 282. <hi>What be the Reaſons of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Will of God ſignified by his Commands; for he having the ſupream and abſolute Authority over us, we are therefore bound to obey him, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.3. &amp; 5.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.4, 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Example of Chriſt, which we are required to follow, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6.</p>
               <p>Q. 283. <hi>What be the Principles of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Obedience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Principles of it are the ſaving Graces of the Spirit of God wrought in the Heart of the Godly, eſpecially Faith, Love and Fear, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7, 8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p>Q. 284. <hi>What be the Properties of this Obedience?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:152928:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a cordial and willing Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, diſcovering it ſelf, 1. By the cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the Heart in obeying God. 2. By the grief of the Heart for diſobedience to God, both in our ſelves, and others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. &amp; 7.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.136.</p>
               <p>Q. 285. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. It is univerſal and compleat, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Obedience of the whole Man, both Soul and Body; an Obedience to the whole Law of God, tho' attended with ſome ſinful Imperfections, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 103.1. &amp; 119.34. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6.</p>
               <p>Q. 286. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a diligent and zealous Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.4. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11.</p>
               <p>Q. 287. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſpeedy &amp; preſent Obedience, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.60. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Q. 288. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a reſolved Obedience againſt all difficulties and diſcouragements, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 24.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.106.</p>
               <p>Q. 289. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a conſtant and perſevering Obedience, at all times, and in all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152928:44"/>to the end of our lives, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.20, 33, 112. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p>Q. 290. <hi>What is the Rule of our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Rule of our Obedience is the Revealed will of God, contained in the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. &amp; 3.16.</p>
               <p>Q. 291. <hi>When do we obey God according to this Rule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we obey God in the Faith of Chriſt, in love and thankfulneſs to Chriſt, in the ſtrength of Chriſt, and in the name of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5.23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15.</p>
               <p>Q. 292. <hi>What are the Ends of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Ends which we ſhould aim at in our Obedience, are 1. The Glory of God, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and 2. The good of our ſelves and others, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination of Thankfulneſs.</head>
               <p>Q. 293. <hi>How may we know our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to be true?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:152928:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By our careful obſerving, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and acknowledging unto God the Bleſſings and Mercies he beſtoweth on us, eſpecially ſpiritual Bleſſings, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.13, 14, 16. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.15.</p>
               <p>Q. 294. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. By our juſt eſtimation or valuing the Bleſſing and Mercies of God, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their worth, excellency and uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.46, 48, 49. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.10, 16.</p>
               <p>Q. 295. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 3. By our dutiful rendring to God according to the Bleſſings received from him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.15.</p>
               <p>Q. 296. <hi>What ſhould a thankful Soul render unto God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. High Praiſes of his Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs, Truth, and of all his Perfections, as alſo of all his Bleſſings &amp; Mercies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2, 3, 4. &amp; 106.1, 2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12, 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Q. 297. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hearty Affections, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.37, 38, 47.</p>
               <p>Q. 298. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Humble Obedience, devoting both our Selves and Services unto God, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Vows, anſwering our Covenant Engagements to him, living to Chriſt, &amp;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152928:45"/>being willing and ready to dye for him, if we be called to it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.38. &amp; 116.14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 25. <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination of Holy Deſires.</head>
               <p>Q. 299. <hi>How may we know whether our Deſire or Appetite to this Holy Supper be true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Cauſes, Objects, Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Companions, and Ends of it.</p>
               <p>Q. 300. <hi>What are the Cauſes of theſe Deſires?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A ſight and ſenſe of our want of this Ordinance, for the ſpiritual Benefits thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſight and ſenſe of the ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fulneſs of this Ordinance, and of Chriſt in it, to ſupply our want, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A taſte or experience of the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt in his Ordinances, and of ſpiritual Refreſhment received by them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2, 3.</p>
               <p>Q. 301. <hi>What is the Object of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or Appetite?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Object of it is not only, nor chiefly the Supper of the Lord, but the Lord of the Supper, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.2. &amp; 63.1.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:152928:46"/>
               <p>Q. 302. <hi>What are the Properties of this Deſire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſtrong deſire, an holy long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Chriſt in this Ordinance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25. &amp; 14.2.</p>
               <p>Q. 303. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is an induſtrious Deſire, or puts the Soul upon pious Endeavours to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Mercies deſired, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.9.</p>
               <p>Q. 304. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It makes the Soul reſtleſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of Delays, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.14.</p>
               <p>Q. 305. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It makes the Soul glad of opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to enjoy Chriſt in his Ordinances, and careful to lay hold on them, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>Q. 306. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It makes Chriſt and his ſpiritual Benefits ſweet and pleaſant to the Soul, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>Q. 307. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It cauſes the Soul to feed heartily on Chriſt in his Ordinances by Faith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6.</p>
               <p>Q. 308. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It makes the Soul willing to part with any thing to obtain Chriſt and his Ordinances, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.11.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:152928:46"/>
               <p>Q. 309. <hi>What be the Companions of this Deſire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. It is accompanied with an high eſteem of Chriſt and his Ordinances, <hi>Job</hi> 23.12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</p>
               <p>Q. 310. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. It is accompanied with a reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or keeping of our ſpiritual Food in the Soul, a digeſting of it, and getting ſpiritual ſtrength by it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4.</p>
               <p>Q. 311. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is accompanied with a readineſs and care to lay out our ſpiritual ſtrength in the Service of Chriſt, from whom we receive it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.3.</p>
               <p>Q. 312. <hi>What is another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is accompanied with love to Chriſt, delight, content and ſatisfaction in Chriſt, though we want this Worlds goods, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>Q. 313. <hi>What is the End of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A gracious Soul deſireth this holy Ordinance, and Chriſt in it, for his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual refreſhment, nouriſhment &amp; growth in Grace, that he may thereby be the better able to ſerve Chriſt in his place and relation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.25, 28, 32.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:152928:47"/>
               <head>The Examination of growth in Grace.</head>
               <p>Q. 314. <hi>How may we know whether we do grow in Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By the increaſe of our ſpiritual Appetites to our ſpiritual Food; or by the increaſe of our deſires after Chriſt, his Word and Ordinances, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 42, 1, and 27.4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd 63.1, 2.</p>
               <p>Q. 315. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. By the increaſe of our ſpiritual ſtrength, to perform Duties, endure Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and reſiſt our Souls Enemies, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Fhil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 138.2.</p>
               <p>Q. 316. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 3. By the increaſe of our ſpiritual ſtature, when we wax bigger and taller in Grace and Holineſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.28. <hi>James</hi> 2.5.</p>
               <p>Q. 317. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 4. By the change of our voice and viſage; when we ſpeak more underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, ſavourily and experimentally of God, and the things of God, and look more like our heavenly Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p>Q. 318. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> 5. By the change of our Carriage and Converſation; when we grow more
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152928:47"/>ſerious, humble, holy, circumſpect and heavenly in our lives, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15.</p>
               <p>Q. 319. <hi>Why ſhould we examine the growth of our Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe God giveth us his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, that we may grow in Grace by the uſe of them, and expects our growth ſhould be ſuitable to the means of Grace which we enjoy, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>Q. 320. <hi>What is another Reaſon of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. Becauſe the growth of our Grace will be a good Evidence to us of the Truth of it; for if we grow, we live, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.3.</p>
               <p>Q. 321. <hi>What is another Reaſon of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 3. Becauſe the Diſcovery of our growth in Grace will quicken and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us in our Attendance on the Means of Grace, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2, 3.</p>
               <p>322. <hi>What if we find that our Graces do not grow, but rather decay?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ought to be deeply humbled for it before the Lord, beg pardon of it, ſearch out the cauſes of it, that they may be removed, and labour to improve God's Ordinances better for time to come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4, 5. &amp; 3.1, 2.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:152928:48"/>
               <p>Q. 323. <hi>What are the cauſes of Decays of Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two eſpecially:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Neglect of Chriſt's Ordinances, the Means of Grace, or uſing of them negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and formally, or without a due care to improve them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Complying with ſome Temptations to Sin, or indulging and nouriſhing ſome Corruption in our Souls.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination of the Grace we want.</head>
               <p>Q. 325. <hi>How may we know what Grace we want?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By looking into our Souls, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what Grace we have already, and whether that be in a growing or decaying ſtate.</p>
               <p>Q. 325. <hi>What are the uſual wants of gracious Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as theſe. They uſually want quickning Grace, and ſtrengthning Grace to enable them to withſtand Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, mortifie Corruptions, perform Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, bear their Burdens, the confirmation of the Covenant of Grace, and of their myſtical Union to Chriſt their Head, the Aſſurance of the Love of God, of an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Chriſt, and his Benefits, and of the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152928:48"/>Pardon of their Sins, and Peace with God through Chriſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.159.28.116. &amp; 35.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.2.</p>
               <p>Q. 326. <hi>Why ſhould we examine our ſelves about our ſpiritual wants before we come to the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is needful that we ſhould come with a due ſenſe of our ſpiritual wants, to this and other Ordinances, and with Deſires and Prayers unto God for the Supplies of them, <hi>John</hi> 5.6. <hi>Luke.</hi> 18.35, 36, 39, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 41. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17, 18.</p>
               <p>Q. 327. <hi>What other Duty ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to fit us for the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould endeavour to get our Graces quickned and ſtirred up in us, or prepared to be acted and exerciſed on their proper Objects, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p>Q 328. <hi>Why ſhould our Graces be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſtirred up before this Ordinance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe our Graces are to be acted and exerciſed in partaking of this holy Ordinance, and ſo need quickning to it.</p>
               <p>Q. 329. <hi>How may our knowledge be quickned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By labouring for a more clear diſtinct and full Knowledge of ſpiritual things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By meditating on thoſe ſpiritual
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152928:49"/>things that we do know, their Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Neceſſity and Uſefulneſs to us.</p>
               <p>Q. 330. <hi>How may Faith be quickned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By feeding on Chriſt in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and meditating on the freeneſs, fulneſs, firmneſs and ſweetneſs of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By conſidering &amp; believing Chriſt's gracious Invitations, and aſſurance of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment and benefit to thoſe that come to him in his own way, <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28. <hi>John</hi> 7.37.</p>
               <p>Q. 331. <hi>How may Repentance be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By ſearching out our ſpecial Sins ſince the laſt Sacrament, confeſſing them to God with ſhame and ſorrow of heart, judging and condemning our ſelves for them, and begging pardon of them, and power againſt them through Grace for time to come, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. <hi>James</hi> 4.9.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.1, 2, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. 332. <hi>How may our Love to God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Spirit be quickned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By meditating on the infinite Love of God the Father, in giving Chriſt; the Love of Chriſt, in giving himſelf to dye for us; and the Love of the Holy Spirit, in revealing Chriſt to us, and in us, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.30.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:152928:49"/>
               <p>Q. 333. <hi>How may our Love to other Chriſtians be quickned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By remembring the New Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt requiring it. 2. By con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering our near and ſpiritual Relation to them, as being our Brethren, and Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members of Chriſt's Myſtical Body. 3. By beholding the Image of God upon them, <hi>John</hi> 13.34. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <p>Q. 334. <hi>How may Love to our Enemies be quickned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By conſidering the Command of Chriſt requiring it. 2. By conſidering the Example of Chriſt, who loved us, when we were his Enemies, ſo as to dye for us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.10.</p>
               <p>Q. 335. <hi>How may our Obedience be quickned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By conſidering the Holineſs, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and goodneſs of Chriſt's Commands. 2. By conſidering the Bleſſings promiſed to the Obedient, and the Puniſhments threatned to the diſobedient, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Job</hi> 36.11, 12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.23.</p>
               <p>Q. 336. <hi>How may our Thankfulneſs to God be quickned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By conſidering the many, great and rich Bleſſings which he hath beſtowed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152928:50"/>on us in the Covenant of Grace. And 2. Our own great unworthineſs of the leaſt of them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8.</p>
               <p>Q. 337. <hi>How may our holy Deſires, or ſpiritual Appetite be quickned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By conſidering our want of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Food, and of refreſhment and Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By conſidering the ſweetneſs, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs and ſufficiency of the ſpiritual Proviſions, which Chriſt hath made for us in this Ordinance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By conſidering the Promiſes which God hath made to refreſh and ſatisfie hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and thirſty Souls, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.17. <hi>John</hi> 6.55.56. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10. &amp; 107.9.</p>
               <p>Q. 338. <hi>What other Duty ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to fit us for the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould ſolemnly ſeek the Lord by Prayer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the pardon of former Neglects of this Ordinance, and ſinful Failings in our partaking of it, and of preſent unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the holy Preparation of our Hearts for this Ordinance, Communion with God in it, and Communications of Grace, and ſpiritual Nouriſhment from
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152928:50"/>him by it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18, 19, 20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.1.</p>
               <p>Q. 339. <hi>Why ſhould we thus ſolemnly ſeek the Lord before this Ordinance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe it is needful both to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie our ſelves for this Ordinance, and to have this Ordinance ſanctified to us; for Prayer is the means to both, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the ſpiritual Benefit of this and all Ordinances comes alone from God, which is to be obtained by Prayer, <hi>James</hi> 1.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p>Q. 340. <hi>What other Duty ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to fit us for the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould hope for and expect God's gracious Anſwer to our Prayers in his meeting and bleſſing us in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 42.5. &amp; 119.166. &amp; 62.5.</p>
               <p>Q. 341. <hi>What ground have we for this hope?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God's holy Word, wherein he hath freely promiſed to meet and bleſs his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in his Ordinance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of our Duties in partaking.</head>
               <p>Q. 342. <hi>What is required of us in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:152928:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:152928:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:152928:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two things eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A ſober and reverent behaviour of the Body.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſerious and gracious diſpoſition of the Soul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12 1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</p>
               <p>Q. 343. <hi>What geſture of Body ſhould we uſe in the Act of Receiving, ſtanding, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or kneeling?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sitting ſeems to be the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Geſture of the Body in the Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, as being moſt agreeable to the Example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, (who ſate, or ſate-leaning) which was then the Table-geſture amongſt the Jews. But Chriſtians ſhould not rigidly impoſe any geſture on each other, nor uncharitably Cenſure each other for difference of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, or Practice in this or ſuch like Circumſtances, if a due Reverence be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.20. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.18, 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.2, 5, 23, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</p>
               <p>Q. 344. <hi>Wherein conſiſts the gracious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition of the Soul in partaking of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. In coming to this holy Ordinance with a deep, ſelf-humbling ſenſe of our own vileneſs and unworthineſs of ſo great a Priviledge, becauſe of our ſins, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.19.</p>
               <p>Q. 345. <hi>Wherein elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:152928:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. In animating at right ends in the uſe of this Ordinance, ſuch as the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Remembrance of Chriſt, our ſpiritual Nouriſhment, and growth in Grace; the confirming of the Covenant of Grace; the teſtifying of our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to Chriſt; and the ſtrengthning of our Union to him and Communion with him, and with one another.</p>
               <p>Q. 346. <hi>Wherein elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 3. In uſing this Ordinance accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſt's Inſtitution in order to theſe Ends; that is, uſing the ſame Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Bread and Wine, and the ſame Words and Actions about them, and to the ſame ſignifications and ends that Chriſt uſed them for.</p>
               <p>Q. 347. <hi>Wherein elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 4. In holy Meditations on the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Words, and Actions that are uſed in the Celebration or Adminiſtration of this holy Ordinance, and eſpecially on Chriſt himſelf, who is ſignified and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.1. <hi>John</hi> 1.29.</p>
               <p>Q. 348. <hi>What good Meditations may our Souls raiſe from theſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. When we ſee Bread and Wine prepared for this Ordinance, we ſhould meditate on the Reſemblance that there
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152928:53"/>is between them and the Body and Blood of Chriſt ſignified by them.</p>
               <p>Q. 349. <hi>How doth Bread reſemble the Body of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In three things eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As Corn is prepared by grinding, moulding and baking, to make it Bread for our Bodies, ſo Chriſt was prepared by exquiſite Sufferings to be Bread for our Souls, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10.</p>
               <p>Q. 350. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As Bread is the Staff and ſtrength of our Natural Life, ſo is Chriſt the Staff and Strength of our ſpiritual Life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>05.16. &amp; 19.14.</p>
               <p>Q. 351. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 3. As Bread is but one Body, tho' it be made up of many Grains, ſo Chriſt myſtical (that is the Church) is but one Body, though made up of many Members, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.</p>
               <p>Q. 352. <hi>How doth the Wine reſemble the Blood of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In three things eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As Wine quencheth the Thirſt of the Body, ſo doth the Blood of Chriſt quench the Thirſt of the Soul, <hi>John</hi> 6.35.</p>
               <p>Q. 353. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. As Wine is of a cheering Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152928:53"/>making the Heart glad; ſo the Blood of Chriſt, applied by Faith, cheers and makes glad the Souls of mournful ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15.</p>
               <p>Q. 354. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 3. As Wine is of a purging and cleanſing quality, ſo the Blood of Chriſt doth meritoriouſly purge and cleanſe us from ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13, 14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7.</p>
               <p>Q. 355. <hi>What other Meditation may we raiſe from this Ordinance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we ſee the Bread and Wine bleſſed, ſanctified, or ſet apart from a common to an holy uſe, by the Miniſters pronouncing the words of Inſtitution, and Prayer, we ſhould meditate on God the Father his ſanctifying, and ſetting apart his Son, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, from all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, to be our Redeemer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1.</p>
               <p>Q. 356. <hi>What other Meditation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we ſee the Bread broken, we ſhould meditate on the Breaking of Chriſt's ſacred Body on the Croſs, and all the Sufferings, Pains and Torments which he endured both in Soul and Body for our ſakes, on the heinous nature of our ſins, that could not be done away, but by the ſhedding of Chriſt's Blood; and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Juſtice of God the Father in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152928:54"/>his only begotten Son, when he ſtood as our Surety.</p>
               <p>Q 357. <hi>What other Meditation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we ſee the Miniſter offering and giving Bread and Wine to us, we ſhould meditate on the infinite Love of God the Father in Giving Chriſt, and of Chriſt in Giving himſelf to be a Sacrifice for us, and of the Spirit in revealing and applying Chriſt to us.</p>
               <p>Q. 258. <hi>What other Meditation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When we Receive the Bread and Wine from the hand of the Miniſter, with the hand of our Bodies, and eat and drink them with our Mouths, we ſhould medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the ſpiritual Receiving of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Chriſt, and feeding on him by Faith in our Souls.</p>
               <p>Q. 359. <hi>What other Meditation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould meditate on the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Benefits that redound to true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers by a right receiving of Chriſt in this holy Ordinance, which are Redemption from all Enemies and Evils, Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, Pardon of Sin, Juſtification, Adoption, Sanctification, Victory over our Souls Adverſaries, Increaſe of Grace, and a Title to Glory.</p>
               <p>Q. 360. <hi>Wherein elſe doth this gracious diſpoſition of Soul conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:152928:54"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 5. In a lively acting or exerciſing of ſaving Graces, and uſing our bodily ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſeeing, touching, and taſting to help our ſpiritual Senſes and Graces in their Actings, <hi>John</hi> 20.27.</p>
               <p>Q. 361. <hi>What Graces ſhould we exerciſe in partaking of this Ordinance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould eſpecially exerciſe theſe four, Faith, Repentance, Love and Joy.</p>
               <p>Q. 362. <hi>How is Faith to be exerciſed in it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Faith ſhould be exerciſed as the Eye of the Soul, to diſcern Chriſt in this Ordinance, as the hand of the Soul, to Receive him, and as the Mouth of the Soul, to feed upon him, or apply him with all his Benefits to each Believer in particular, <hi>Job</hi> 20.28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
               <p>Q. 363. <hi>How is Repentance to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Repentance ſhould then be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in remembring our ſins, confeſſing them with ſhame and ſorrow, hating of them, judging and condemning our ſelves for them, and turning from them unto God in Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4, 5.6. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10, 11.</p>
               <p>Q. 364. <hi>How is Love to God then to be exerciſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:152928:55"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Love to God; both Father, Son, and Spirit ſhould then be exerciſed by the fervent out goings of the Soul to God, and to each Perſon in the God head, and by the firm cleaving of the Soul to him, as to the chief Good, and our All-ſufficient Portion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23.</p>
               <p>Q. 365. <hi>How is Love to other Chriſtians then to be exerciſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Love to other Chriſtians ſhould then be exerciſed by our cleaving to them in heart, as to our Brethren, by praying with and for them, by forgiving their Treſpaſſes againſt us, and by a readineſs to give to thoſe that want, according to our Ability, and their Neceſſity, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32.</p>
               <p>Q. 366. <hi>How is Joy then to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Joy is then to be exerciſed in the Soul's being cheered, revived, and lifted up in the believing apprehenſion, or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of its intereſt in God, as his own God in Chriſt and Covenant, and ſo in all the Bleſſings promiſed in the Covenant of Grace, of which this Ordinance is a ſign and ſeal, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2.</p>
               <p>Q. 367. <hi>How is this Ordinance to be eloſed up?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:152928:55"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is to be cloſed up in ſinging ſome Spiritual Hymn to the praiſe of God our Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.30. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of our Duties after partaking.</head>
               <p>Q. 368. <hi>What is required of us after partaking of tho Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two ſorts of Duties, ſome more publick, and others more private.</p>
               <p>Q. 369. <hi>What are the publick Duties?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A ſolemn and hearty Thankſgiving to God for his love in giving Chriſt, for Chriſt's love in giving himſelf, and for the love of the holy Spirit in revealing Chriſt to us, and in us, with all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fruits of this Love. As alſo for the Covenant of Grace, the Seals of it, and Spiritual benefit by them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12.</p>
               <p>Q. 370 <hi>What is another publick Duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 2. A ſincere renewing our Conſent to the Covenant of Grace, and yielding our ſelves to the Lord as his Covenant-Servants, with holy purpoſes of new and better Obedience to him in the ſtrenght of Chriſt for time to come, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.3. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13. c. 12.1. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.8, 32.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:152928:56"/>
               <p>Q. 371. <hi>What is another publick Duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A cheerful giving ſome Relief to the poor Members of Jeſus Chriſt, in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of our Love and Thankfulneſs to Chriſt for the Mercy we have received from him, and of our Love to them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40.</p>
               <p>Q. 372. <hi>What are the private Duties af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are two eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A diligent Inquiry, Whether we have received any ſpiritual Comfort or Benefit by this Ordinance; <hi>i. e.</hi> Whether our Graces have been ſtrengthned, our Souls refreſhed, nouriſhed, revived, and cheered, our Conſciences pacified, and our Aſſurance of the Love of God increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. 373. <hi>What if we cannot find any of theſe Spiritual Benefits?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould ſearch out the Cauſe, whether it was not want of due prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before, or want of a right diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the partaking of it; and if ſo, we ſhould confeſs it unto God, and be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for it, endeavouring by after pains in Humiliation and Prayer, to obtain the efficacy and benefit of it.</p>
               <p>Q. 374. <hi>What if we did our beſt in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152928:56"/>preparing for it, and in partaking of it, and yet are not ſenſible of any real Benefit or Comfort by it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould pray earneſtly to God, and wait patiently on him for the Benefit and Comfort of this Ordinance, becauſe as Phyſick doth not preſently work, nor Meat preſently nouriſh, ſo neither doth this or other Ordinances always preſently benefit our Souls, but in God's time they ſhall.</p>
               <p>Q. 375. <hi>What if we do find preſent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and Comfort by it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould thankfully acknowledge it to God, and labour to preſerve it by an holy, humble, and watchful Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15.</p>
               <p>Q. 376. <hi>What is the other Duty after the Lord's Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A faithful keeping Covenant with God, yielding a ready, cheerful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Obedience to all his Commandments in Heart, Lip and Life, watching and praying againſt ſin, reſiſting its motions and temptations, exerciſing Grace, laying hold on Opportunities of honouring God, in doing or receiving Good, endeavouring to be perfect in every Good Work, to do his Will, that our Fruit may be unto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152928:57"/>and the end Eternal Life, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22.</p>
               <p>Q. 377. <hi>Why ſhould we be thus careful to keep Covenant with God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe we cannot otherwiſe juſtly expect God ſhould keep Covenant with us, or that he ſhould give us the Bleſſings promiſed, unleſs we give him the Obedience commanded, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe elſe we ſhould but mock God in making Covenant with him, and in receiving the Signs and Seals of it, and deceive our own Souls, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.30.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becanſe we ſhould elſe deprive our ſelves of the ſpiritual Benefits of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and expoſe our ſelves to God's juſt Diſpleaſure, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29, 30. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.4, 5.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:57"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of <hi>BOOKS</hi> ſold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappel in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>OF Thoughtfulneſs for the Morrow; with an Appendix concerning the immoderate Deſire of fore-knowing Things to come.</item>
               <item>of Charity, in reference to other Mens Sins.</item>
               <item>A Sermon at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Rich. Adams,</hi> M. A. ſometime Fellow of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen-Noſe</hi> Colledge, in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Redeemer's Tears wept over loſt Souls; in a Treatiſe on <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. with an Appendix, wherein ſomewhat is occaſionally diſcourſed, concerning the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and how God is ſaid to will the Salvation of them that periſh.</item>
               <item>A Sermon directing what we are to do after a ſtrict Enquiry, whether or no we truly love God.</item>
               <item>A Funeral Sermon for Mrs. <hi>Eſther Sampſon,</hi> the late Wife of <hi>Hen. Sampſon,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152928:58"/>Doctor of Phyſick, who died <hi>Nov.</hi> 24. 1689.</item>
               <item>The Carnality of Religious Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In two Sermons preached at the Merchants Lecture in <hi>Broad-ſtreet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon for <hi>Reformation of Manners.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon Preach'd on the Day of Thankſgiving, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 2. 1697. To which is prefix'd Dr. <hi>Bate's</hi> Congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Speech to the KING.</item>
               <item>A Calm and Sober Enquiry, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Poſſibility of a Trinity in the Godhead.</item>
               <item>A Letter to a Friend, concerning a Poſtſcript to the Defence of Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Notion of the Trinity in Unity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the calm and ſober Enquiry up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ſubject.</item>
               <item>A View of that part of the late Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to <hi>H. H.</hi> about the Trinity; which concerns the ſober Enquiry on that Subject.</item>
               <item>The Redeemers Dominion over the Invinſible World.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> Funeral Sermon.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Matthew Meads</hi> Funeral Sermon. All 15 by the Reverend <hi>John Howe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fountain of Life opened, or a Diſplay of Chriſt in his Eſſential and
<pb facs="tcp:152928:58"/>Mediatorial Glory. Containing Forty two Sermons on various Texts.</item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of the Soul of Man, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Divine Original, Excellent and Immortal Nature of the Soul are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Method of Grace, in bringing home the Eternal Redemption, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd by the Father, and accompliſh'd by the Son, through the Effectual Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Spirit unto God's Elect. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 2d. part of the Fountain of Life.</item>
               <item>The Divine Conduct, or Myſtery of Providence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Navigation Spiritualiz'd: Or, a new Compaſs for Sea-men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two Treatiſes, the firſt of Fear; the ſecond, the Righteous Man's Refuge in the Evil Day.</item>
               <item>A Saint indeed: The great Work of a Chriſtian.</item>
               <item>A Touchſtone of Sincerity: Or, Signs of Grace, and Simptoms of Hypocriſie: Being the Second Part of the Saint in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</item>
               <item>A Token for Mourners: Or, Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries for Sorrow for the Death of Friends.</item>
               <item>Husbandry ſpiritualiz'd; or the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb facs="tcp:152928:59"/>Uſe of Earthly Things. All theſe 10 by Mr. <hi>John Flavel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sermons and Diſcourſes on ſeveral Divine ſubjects, by the late reverend and learned Divine Mr. <hi>David Clarkson</hi> B. D. ſometime Fellow of <hi>Clare-hall, Cambridge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s Annotations on the Bible, 2 Vol. 3d Edit. with an Addition of a Concordance and Contents to each chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; by Mr. <hi>Sam. Clark.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Catholick Theology</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Methodus Theologica,</hi> both by Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ſacred Poem on the Glory of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Strong</hi> on the Covenant</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Burgeſs</hi> on the <hi>Corinthians</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Taylor</hi> on Chriſt's temptation</item>
               <item>A Dialogue between <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> about the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gurnall</hi>'s chriſtian Armour</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Horton</hi>'s 100 Sermons</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Noſtredamus</hi>'s Prophecies</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Melvill</hi>'s Memoirs</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>'s Poems</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daille</hi> on the <hi>Colloſſians</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clark</hi>'s Martyrology</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:59"/>
               <item>The Acts, Deciſions, Decrees, and Canons of the reformed Churches, in <hi>France;</hi> being a moſt faithful and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Hiſtory of the Riſe, Growth, and Decay of the Reformation in that Kingdom; their confeſſion of Faith, Speeches, Letters, caſes of conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Quick</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Church-Hiſtory and Councils.</item>
               <item>—Hiſtory of councils inlarged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended</item>
               <item>—Apology for Nonconformiſts</item>
               <item>—Second Defence of Nonconſormiſts</item>
               <item>—Apology againſt Eight Men</item>
               <item>—Treatiſe of Epiſcopacy</item>
               <item>—Diſputations of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               <item>—Life of Faith; firſt of the Sermons preach'd before King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond.</item>
               <item>—<hi>Engliſh</hi> Nonconformity</item>
               <item>—Naked Popery</item>
               <item>—againſt <hi>Dodwell</hi> and <hi>Sherlock</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Which is the True Church</item>
               <item>—Catholick communion, againſt both Extreams, in ſix ſeveral controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</item>
               <item>—Moral Prognoſtication</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:60"/>
               <item>—Search for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Schiſmaticks.</item>
               <item>—Farewel Sermon, publiſhed by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</item>
               <item>—Mr. <hi>John Corbet</hi>'s Funeral Sermon</item>
               <item>—Glorious Kingdom of Chriſt</item>
               <item>—Reply to Mr. <hi>Tho. Beverly</hi>'s Anſwer.</item>
               <item>—National churches</item>
               <item>—Church-concord</item>
               <item>—Penitent confeſſion, and neceſſary Vindication</item>
               <item>—Power of a chriſtian Magiſtrate</item>
               <item>—Diſputations of right to Sacraments.</item>
               <item>—Diſputation of Juſtification</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ark</hi> on the Covenant</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brown</hi>'s Goſpel churches</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bulley</hi> on the Covenant</item>
               <item>—Critical Enqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chariton</hi>'s Enquiries into humane Nature</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clarkſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi>'s practical Divinity of papiſts</item>
               <item>—No Evidence for Dioceſan churches</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rbet</hi>'s Nonconformiſt's Plea</item>
               <item>A Dialogue between a Proteſtant and a Jew, and a Papiſt and a Jew.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oolittle</hi>'s Proteſtant's Anſwer to, <hi>Where was your Church before</hi> Luther.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elton</hi> on the Commandments.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fryfell</hi>'s Sermons of Grace and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humphry</hi>'s Mediocria compleat</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:60"/>
               <item>—Peaceable Diſquiſition</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hales</hi> of Religion</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hudſon</hi> on the Church</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hierome</hi>'s Life</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Laroque</hi> on the Euchariſt</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Education of Gentlewomen</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgan</hi>'s Dyalling</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Manning</hi> of Predetermination</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mead</hi>'s Viſion of the Wheels.</item>
               <item>—Sermon at the Union</item>
               <item>Morning Exerciſe againſt Popery</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Muſe</hi>'s Alphabet</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Owen</hi>'s ſeaſonable Words for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants.</item>
               <item>Preſent Nonconformiſts Vindicated</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pool</hi>'s Apology for Religion</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Owen</hi> of being ſpiritually-minded</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Rowlandſon</hi>'s captivity</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wadſworth</hi>'s Separation no Schiſm</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nock</hi> of Regeneration</item>
               <item>True Ceſs, or intrinſick Value of all real Eſtates.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Officium Cleri deſiderium Populi</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Troughton</hi>'s Apology for Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Yarranton</hi>'s <hi>England's</hi> Improvement</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hodges</hi>'s two Sermons</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phelps</hi> Innocency rewarded</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mall</hi>'s Axe at the Root</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:61"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Smith</hi>'s chriſtians Work, at <hi>Sorrell</hi>'s Funeral.</item>
               <item>State of bleſſedneſs</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vincent</hi> at <hi>Bakers</hi> Funeral</item>
               <item>—at <hi>Jaueway</hi>'s Funeral</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hudſon</hi> at <hi>Shute</hi>'s Funeral</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lloyd</hi>'s Death of God's <hi>Moſes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whittaker</hi>'s Funeral Sermon</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scot</hi>'s Saint's privilege by dying</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wadſworth</hi>'s Funeral Sermon</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>Stilling fleet</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Remarks on Affairs of Trade</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Waller</hi>'s Effays</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Claud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>'s Defence of Reformation</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wallis</hi>'s Theological Diſcourſes on ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Occaſions in two Parts</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jackſons</hi>'s Annotations on the Bible</item>
               <item>—on <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Woodward</hi>'s Call to Humiliation, for the grievous Sin of Perſecution</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Boyſe</hi>'s Sermons againſt Quenching the Holy Spirit</item>
               <item>Vanity, Danger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of continuing Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in the Worſhip of God.</item>
               <item>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory of <hi>France</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ellis</hi>'s <hi>Engliſh</hi> School</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grew</hi>'s Parable of the prodigal</item>
               <item>Preſent State of <hi>New-England</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hayter</hi> on the <hi>Revelations</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:61"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lightfoot in Lucam</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phelps</hi> on the <hi>Revelations</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Grace and Duty of Heavenly Minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</item>
               <item>The Cauſes, Ways and Means of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Mind of God revealed in his Word.</item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of Apoſtacy</item>
               <item>An Anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to Dr. <hi>Parker</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Humble Teſtimony</item>
               <item>—of Temptation</item>
               <item>—of the Trinity. Theſe 7 by Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſes concerning the actual Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God; in three parts. The firſt, treating concerning the Notion of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſecond, concerning the Specialities of it. The third, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the hard chapters of it. In 53 Sermons.</item>
               <item>Intercourſes of Divine Love betwixt Chriſt and the Church; in two Vol. The firſt, containing fixty one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on the firſt chapter of the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi> The ſecond containing about 47 Sermons on the ſecond chapter of the <hi>Canticles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Reaſonable Account, why ſome pious Nonconforming Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152928:62"/>judge it ſinful for them to perform their Miniſterial Acts in publick ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Prayer, by the preſcribed Forms of others.</item>
               <item>—His Supplement to his reaſonable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe againſt Tranſubſtantiation.</item>
               <item>The Vindication of Litur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, lately publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Faulkner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oved no Vindication.</item>
               <item>Defenſative Armour againſt four of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans moſt fiery Darts, <hi>viz.</hi> Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to Atheiſtical and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Thoughts, Self-Murther, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair and Preſumption. The above 8 by Dr. <hi>John Collings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Allen</hi>'s Alarm to unconverted ſinners.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bury</hi>'s Husbandman's companion</item>
               <item>—Help to Holy walking</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Corbet</hi>'s Kingdom of God among Men</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clarkſon</hi> of ſaving Grace</item>
               <item>—A Diſcourſe concerning Liturgies</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Calamy</hi> of Meditation</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Doolittle</hi>'s Catechiſm</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chorley</hi>'s Memorial of the Bible</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ellis</hi>'s Kingdom of God</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Farthing</hi>'s ſhort Hand</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aeſop</hi> improved, or 300 Fables para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſed.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:62"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Finch</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>Tho. Grantham</hi>'s Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue between a Baptiſt and a Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> of Chriſt's ſatisfaction, tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Green</hi>'s Corruption of Man by Nature</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Burkit</hi> of Infant-baptiſm</item>
               <item>—Sure Mercies of <hi>David</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Baptiſmal bonds renewed</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hurſt</hi>'s Revival of Grace</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hugh</hi>'s Summons to Sinners to think and turn.</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Kidder</hi> on the Saerament</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lorimor</hi>'s Diſeourſes on the Five Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi>'s Intereſt of <hi>Ireland</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Grammer</item>
               <item>—<hi>Veſtibulum Technicum</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nomenclatura Mundi</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mead</hi>'s Good of early Obedience</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſs's Myſtagogus Poeticus</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whittaker</hi>'s 18 Sermons</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Steel,</hi> of Old Age</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Staunton</hi>'s Life, with his Dialogues.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roberts</hi> on the Sacrament</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swinnock</hi> on the Attributes</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Norman</hi>'s Caſes of Conſcience</item>
               <item>Whole Duty of Man: Second Part.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barret</hi> on the Covenant</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:152928:63"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wilſon</hi>'s Scripture-Genuine-Interpreter</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Waſe</hi>'s Grammer</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shaw</hi>'s true Chriſtian's Teſt, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Watſon</hi>'s Sermons on <hi>Malachy</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Charles Wolſely</hi>'s Mount of Spirits</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vincent</hi> of Conſcience</item>
               <item>—Touchſtone of Grace and Nature</item>
               <item>—Converſion of the Soul</item>
               <item>—Chriſt's ſudden appearance to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Burgeſs</hi>'s Characters of a Godly Man</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ottee's</hi> Sermons</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Melius inquirendum,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wadſwoth</hi>'s Immortality of the Soul</item>
               <item>—Faith's Triumph</item>
               <item>Hiſtory of Cardinal <hi>Ximenes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stedman</hi> of Union</item>
               <item>—Sober ſingularity</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ars Sciendi, ſive Logica</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Venning</hi> of Sin</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Polwheel</hi> againſt quenching the Spirit</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marſhal</hi>'s Goſpel-Myſtery of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maſon</hi>'s Spiritual Songs, or Songs of Praiſe.</item>
               <item>—his Penitential Crys</item>
               <item>A Funeral Sermon at the Death of Mr. <hi>Joſeph Barret;</hi> with his Life and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:152928:63"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
